Okay, good morning. We are live in
Beijing.
Welcome to our very first YouTube live
stream.
First, I want to thank Carol
of the Yale-Beijing Center. She and her
team have put everything together. And
it's been a fantastic
two weeks with Carol and her team. So,
thanks so much Carol for putting this
together. I would also like to thank
everyone who is in the room today. Some
of you Some of you have come a very long
way. I promise you this will be a very
interesting class. I hope this is a
life-transforming experience
for you. Dante is the greatest writer of
all time. And third, I would thank
everyone who is participating in the
live stream all around the world. We are
having someone monitor the chat. So, if
you have a question, feel free to ask a
question on chat and we'll respond in
real time. So,
we'll begin class, but first I would
like to introduce Carol
and maybe introduce your beautiful
center.
>> Thank you. Thank you, John.
So, hello and welcome.
My name is Carol Lee Rafferty.
I am a Yale College alumna and John's
classmate.
>> Yep.
>> For the
>> We We We saw each each other at Yale.
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> For those new to Yale Center Beijing,
Yale Center Beijing since 2014 is Yale
University's first university-wide
center outside of its campus
and a place for intellectual dialogue
and the exchange of ideas.
Through workshops such as today's,
we seek [clears throat] to advance the
Yale University mission to create,
disseminate, and preserve knowledge.
So, why are we here?
Jeong and I were classmates and
schoolmates about 25 years ago.
We are now both parents of three
children.
>> Yep.
>> And like many parents,
we um wish to
not only pass on knowledge to the next
generation,
but also wisdom.
A deeper understanding of what it means
to be human.
Yale's motto is lux et veritas in Latin
and urim vetummim in Hebrew,
which means light and truth.
So, through the exploration of Dante and
the great books, we hope you will
encounter
beauty, light, and truth,
and also be able to wrestle with
humanity's oldest questions.
What does it mean to be human? How
should we live?
What is worth striving for?
Um and that's why we're so excited to be
doing this workshop together.
>> And Dante will answer these questions.
>> Yeah.
And without further ado, I'll turn back
to um Jeong and begin our journey with
Dante and the great books.
>> Okay. Thank you so much. Okay. So, um as
you can see from the screen, we will be
using um
this website that anyone can use. It's
all free. Uh the website address is
there.
Um so, the Divine Comedy is divided into
three parts: Inferno, Purgatorio, and
Paradiso.
What we will do,
um um, which is very strange, is we
we are going to actually start in part
three. It will become obvious to you
over time why we're doing that, okay?
So, today we are going to start with
canto one of Paradiso. And the
translation we will use is Mandelbaum,
I'll let it Mandelbaum. So, if you are
watching this on the live stream, please
go to the website or you can just
actually just watch the screen because
you watch we will have the entire text
on the screen. But, this web this
resource is extremely valuable,
um, and we will be using it this entire
two weeks.
Okay.
So, the first thing I asked you guys to
do was write one paragraph about what
heaven is.
Do we have any volunteers who can share?
Yes.
What is Yes, go ahead, please.
>> Um, so
>> And you need to either use a handheld or
press down on one of your mics. Yeah.
Uh, continuously. Thanks.
>> Uh, heaven is a place of fulfillment,
peace, and harmony where every entity
can coexist. Negative feelings and
behavior do not occur.
Uh, we feel elevated by the fact that it
feels like a destination and we are the
best versions of ourselves.
Uh, it's like we're above
uh, all what we have been through to
only keep the best.
Heaven has more to my eyes of a feeling
aspect than a visual one.
Uh, I could still imagine having a
bright, vibrant colors, uh, flowers, and
animals.
>> Great, that's beautiful. Thank you so
much.
Anyone else? Yes.
>> Uh, personally I do not believe in the
existence of heaven. Or, if by some
chance it does exist, I do not believe
in its ubiquity.
>> Yeah, that's not the answer I want,
though.
>> Um,
yeah, well, that doesn't surprise me as
I didn't really know what you were going
to want.
Um if there exists a heaven in any means
of the word for any religion, I would
think that it's a place of joy, but also
of exclusion and stagnation. The ideas
of heaven are so radically different
from one religion to another that
reconciliation seems impossible. In
which case, heaven must be segregated.
There is no change in heaven, it being
definition a deathless and perfect
place. And so heaven is stagnation.
Heaven is a construct comprised of the
idea of what is good held by each
individual faithful. It is not
essentially good except to the one who
created it. It is the ultimate
expression of life faith.
>> Okay. Um so that's very interesting
because to answer this question, you're
using logic and reason. And this is
something that they might ask you to do
on
on AP literature examination.
For this class, if we're truly to
embrace Dante, we have to use our
intuition and imagination, okay? That's
That's something that um will become
much more clear as we read Dante, but
the imagination is what will lead you to
a truth, all right? Uh we have we have
someone here? Yes?
>> Um to me, paradise is a place for
eternal pea- peace and happiness.
There's no past and future, just
eternal.
Everyone there are full of meaning and
purpose. The kind of joy and beauty in
heaven is unfathomable. All the love and
consciousness is intertwined together.
>> That's beautiful, yeah. So perfection,
something that is pure joy,
uh beyond our imagination.
Yeah, good. Anyone else?
Uh yes?
>> I think it's where God is. So it's the
typical Christian and Catholic view of
life everlasting in the presence of God.
Eternal life singing and worshipping God
and doing whatever you love most in your
little house and mansion that God has
rewarded you based on what you have done
in your present life, I guess.
>> Yeah, so that's very interesting because
what you just said is exactly what
Augustine wrote in The City of God. He
explained
heaven as a place where you are right
beside God and you're all singing
together in unison. Have you read
Augustine before?
>> No.
>> Okay, well that's a very Augustinian
answer. Yes?
>> Hello, can you hear me?
>> [clears throat]
>> I think heaven's for us to meet God and
to have a spiritual and intellectual
connection with God and other divine
forces. It's a place where we put down
our ego and fear and engage in the act
of a salvation and personal
enlightenment.
>> Good, yeah. So ego and fear are things
that bind us to this material world.
Thank you. Yes?
>> Okay, you hear me? Okay. So as if I were
to inhabit and maybe Bruce Lee would
lead me to the Kung Fu universe.
Cuz I'm a big fan of Bruce Lee and Kung
Fu and his philosophy and I could see my
grandma and her smiling at me and
embrace me into the arms. And I also can
see the tree light stuffs and wish can
let people see the messages from the
living world. And people who come from
the living world would be nice to come
to this new world and since there's no
rule, no law, but only the people who
believe in your faith and destiny.
And meanwhile I also can sense the God
or Buddha or like who is sitting right
there and keep lecturing to the people
with the wisdom and sauce. And of course
there was a boat which can transfer
people from the dark city
to other shores. And there must be a
lady like beauty who spent the surprise
happiness and marriage seems to all of
them. And the people who want to fly
must be permitted so they could fly high
above the ocean. And lastly, when I was
in that world and there was no flash, no
so people don't need to worry about
overweight or ugly look of look since
everyone looked as light ball or
luminous existence. So that is my
imagination.
>> Yeah, that's very interesting. So what
you're saying is that heaven is
individualized, meaning that whatever
you perceive it is, it becomes. Okay,
that's a very interesting idea. Any more
ideas?
Okay.
All right, good. All right. So, let's
begin, all right? So, we're going to go
to
Canto 1 of Paradise. And we're going to
use the Mandelbaum
um trans
uh
lation. And to set context, again, there
are three different parts to the Divine
Comedy. There's Inferno, there's
Purgatory, and then there is Paradise.
And what's happening is that the Divine
Comedy, it is a pilgrim's journey
where Dante is traveling across the
universe in order to meet God. And he
now has reached Paradise. And his guide
in Paradise uh is Beatrice, his
long-lost love.
And now they are
um flying throughout the cosmos on their
way to meet God. And the um heavens is
divided into nine different spheres,
okay? And the point I'm going to make is
that Dante's perception
or conception of the heavens is unique.
No one else has imagined heaven the way
that Dante has.
And no one will probably ever imagine
the way uh that he has, okay? So, what
we're what we're what we're what we're
going to try and do these first two days
is try to figure out what Dante's
cosmology is. What is his understanding
of the heavens is, and why he has
constructed the heavens in the way that
he has, okay? So, for the first day,
we're going to go very slowly. We're
going to establish the themes, the
motives, the concepts that are going to
help us truly understand
uh the Divine Comedy, okay? So, um
Carol, could you please go ahead and
read the first three lines? The concept,
yes.
>> The glory
The glory of
Is it picking up? Okay.
The glory of the one who moves all
things.
For me, it fills the universe and glows
in one part more and in another less.
>> Wait. All right. So,
um we're going to analyze these three
lines. But before I do so, I want to
introduce you to two literary concepts
that we that will be using a lot uh when
we analyze the Divine Comedy. The first
is the idea of paradox.
And this is actually the main literary
device that Dante will use for the
Divine Comedy, where things are not as
simple as they seem. There's a
contradiction in the idea, and it is
your responsibility to try to unpack or
reconcile the contradiction. And through
this process, it is going to heighten
your imagination and draw you closer to
God, okay? So, so this is the main
literary device we're analyzing
throughout these two
two weeks, the idea of paradox. Second
idea that we'll be looking at is
possibilities.
Possibilities are created by two
concepts, ambiguity
as well as economy. Economy, for those
of you who study poetry, it just means
to use as few words as possible to
describe as much as possible. Ambiguity
means that a sentence or word can can
can contain multiple meanings.
Okay? So, these are the two major
literary devices we'll be studying
um
in the Divine Comedy. So, first question
is
what's the paradox in these three lines?
What's the paradox here? Yes?
>> Well, I'm just shooting in the dark
here. I'm not sure if I'm right, but I
would think that the glory of the one
who moves all things. By definition, God
is omnipotent and omnipresent. However,
it says in the third line that it
permeates the universe and it goes in
one part more and in another less,
meaning that there's inequality even in
heaven.
>> Yeah, that's exactly correct. Okay,
that's a paradox. God can be everywhere
at once, yet there are certain parts
where he
is more and certain parts there is less.
That is a contradiction. That is a
paradox. Why would God, who is
all-knowing,
all-seeing,
all-powerful, why would the universe be
constructed in a way like this? Okay,
that's the central paradox that the
divine comedy is trying to address.
But then, what are the possibilities?
How can we reconcile this paradox?
Uh yes?
>> I think that it's uh maybe present Oh,
sorry. I think maybe it's because like,
for example, God is more present in
heaven, but for example, in the inferno,
we can because I tried the inferno
actually and I can clearly see that like
God's presence is less there, so maybe
we can reconcile this way. So, I think
that this this doesn't contradict with
his like omnipotence or his
omnipresence. It just means that um
she's more concentrated in the certain
like
um
dimension.
>> Right. But then the question then is
like, why does heaven and hell exist?
God can make everything perfect, right?
So, why not why not just make everything
heaven? Why does heaven hell exist?
Uh yes?
>> Because in theology, that would be the
lack of God or the lack of God's
presence. So, there's free choice and
free wills, so that should be a heaven
and a hell.
>> Yeah, that that's the correct answer.
Yes, there has to be If you are to allow
for free will, you must allow for heaven
and hell to exist. Can you explain why?
>> Because if everything is heaven then
there is no free choice. If there is
choice then there will be consequence
and there will be the wrong choice, I
guess. And what happens with the wrong
wrong choice is probably hell or the
lack of God's presence.
>> Anyone else?
Uh yes.
>> Yeah, maybe I think because we are just,
you know, you you're flesh, you're body.
So, if you we got body then we must be
locked, right? Cuz
we can't just get out of it. But if if
there's possibility that people can get
out of your body. Try to imagine, okay,
I used to have such kind of nightmare
when I was,
you know, sleeping in my bed bed and I
thought I was just out of there, out of
my body. That really make me feel so so
so so crazy, but what if there's really
possibility that people really can get
out of your body? Just like
consciousness, like, you know, the cloud
service or something. Maybe. So, maybe
that's the reason why they have these
theories because people have their
souls, not only the body, the flesh, but
also got idea.
So, got souls. Maybe if the souls can be
existed into another world, just like
save save the in the cloud service or
what. Maybe.
Yeah, so maybe that is what heaven
means.
Okay, I suppose. Yeah.
>> All right. So, this is
what's it called, paradox in the Divine
Comedy. Why does heaven exist? Why does
hell exist? Okay? And it has to do with
free will.
So, keep this in the back of your mind,
okay? These are the paradoxes being
created and only by deep reflection,
deep observation, by using your
intuition in your in your imagination,
you come to um an answer, okay? So, this
is an essential paradox, okay? We've
established that. Let's keep on going.
Uh
Carol, do you continue reading, please?
>> Um should I do six or
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
I was one of them the heaven that
receives more of his light.
And I saw things that he who from that
height descends
forgets or cannot speak.
When nearing its desired end, our
intellect sinks into an abyss so deep
that memory fails to follow it.
>> Okay, so what Dante is saying here is
that he has reached the heavens
uh which receives more of his light.
And he saw things
that from that height descends, forgets,
or cannot
speak.
Um
How is Dante able
to reach such heights?
There's a paradox here.
What has enabled him to reach such
heights? That that he's able to achieve
heaven. Yes?
>> Is it kind of the inversion because he's
already gone through hell, so he can
then perceive how great heaven is.
>> Yeah, that is a possibility.
Um it is because he suffered pain.
Because he's seen the worst
that he's able to um to see
um heaven. Yes, that's a possibility.
Good. What What are some other
possibilities? Yes?
>> Maybe he has never lost his love for
Beatrice because Beatrice is kind of
like um
like the God sent an angel, so that
reflects like his love for God and like
divine being.
>> That is true. He's never lost his love
his love for Beatrice, and that's why he
is in paradise.
But
so what? What What does love enable you
to do
that allows you to
ascend.
>> I think that God is like the symbol of
love. So, by like loving Beatrice, he's
like
there's like still this
>> Okay. Okay. Let's be careful with
terminology. God cannot be a symbol. God
exists, right?
Okay.
Okay. Keep Keep on going.
>> So, um I'm I mean, I'm not like an
expert on this, but I'm just thinking
that like because like he's always
loving, so he's always like that's kind
of like a virtue, and it's not really
>> Okay. So, I want you guys to think about
this, okay?
Um he's flying,
but what propelled him into flight is
the imagination,
right? Because from that height,
um once you reach a certain height,
you either descend,
or you forget, or you cannot speak.
Meaning, like your imagination has to be
so far
that you might not be able to go any
further, so you just descend, but you
might also forget what you've imagined.
But, the most likely possibility is you
can't even describe in words what you've
imagined, okay?
So, what's really important to
understand is that the divine comedy
comedy comedy is happening both at a
metaphorical as well as a literal level.
Literal in that he actually is in
heaven, but metaphorical in that he's
also imagining all this, and both are
are true at the same time. Okay? And
that's what poetry is. Poetry is both
literal and metaphorical at the same
time. So, I want you guys to keep this
in the back of your mind because it's
very important to fully understand
what's going on.
>> [snorts]
>> Near this end, our intellect sinks into
an abyss so deep that memory fails to
follow it. So,
Dante is imagining the heavens, and he's
reached his desired end, okay? He wants
to be with God, but then his intellect,
the logic,
sinks into an abyss. So, think think of
a stone
that falls into a hole, okay? It's
falling really fast, and the memory is a
bird trying to catch this stone before
it falls.
Okay? So, that's what he's saying. He's
saying the imagination, the memory, are
two different things.
Okay?
Um can you keep on going, uh Carol?
>> Sure.
>> The next three lines.
>> Okay.
Nevertheless, as much as I, within my
mind, could treasure of the holy
kingdom, shall now become the matter of
my song.
>> Keep on going.
>> Oh, good Apollo, for this final task,
make me the vessel of your excellence.
What you, to merit your love floral,
ask.
>> Keep on going.
>> Until this point, one of Parnassus'
peaks sufficed for me,
but now I face the test.
The aidon that is left, I need both
crests.
>> Okay. All right. So, um let me It's
actually context, okay?
There are at least
three Dantes in the Divine Comedy.
Okay? There are at least three Dantes in
the Divine Comedy.
The first is the pilgrim, the
protagonist,
who is on this journey, okay?
That's the first Dante.
The second Dante
is the historical Dante,
the person who actually lived. And the
historical Dante will appear because
he'll bring in some other historical
figures into Divine Comedy. These are
people he knows, okay? That's the second
Dante. There's a third Dante. And who's
the third Dante?
Who is be third Dante?
>> Imaginative.
>> Sorry?
>> Can you explain what that means?
>> Uh impressive.
>> Like who he imagined himself to be like
in or in heaven or in other places like
>> Mhm.
Who's the third Dante?
Yes.
>> Um well, I would think that is he is the
essential poet. Like he is the essence
of the poet. He's the archetype.
>> This is not a hard guys. This is the
third Dante. Who is the third Dante?
The first is the
character, the protagonist. The second
is the historical Dante, the real Dante.
And who's the third Dante?
Yeah?
>> I just like randomly guessing one, the
Dante in the future.
>> This is not a hard question. Yes.
>> Uh the Dante that he imagines himself
as.
>> No, guys.
Guys, there's a third Dante. Yes.
>> Um the reader.
>> The reader? No, we're the reader.
So, who's the who who's the third Dante?
>> Uh maybe the Holy Father, Holy Spirit.
>> No, no, no, no. No, guys. This is not
hard.
There's a third Dante. Who is the third
Dante?
>> The writer? The author?
>> The writer.
The guy who wrote this thing, okay?
These are not the same people. There is
the protagonist. There is the historical
Dante. And there's the writer, the poet,
okay?
Let me ask you this question.
If it is true that Dante is protagonist,
then who's the antagonist?
Right?
In a book, you have protagonist, you
have an antagonist.
Protagonist is Dante. Who's the
antagonist?
>> Satan.
>> Not Satan. We're in heaven. Satan
doesn't exist in heaven.
Yes?
>> Maybe his old self or something like
that.
>> Yes, exactly. He explained this.
>> When some people enter heaven, he's a
new made man. So, that means he has to
die to his old self to enter into this
new form of pure existence.
>> Yeah. So, the idea here is that the
conflict is between himself, okay? There
is the Dante, the pilgrim,
uh who is trying to seek God. But,
there's Dante the pilgrim who has ego
and fear and doubts, okay? And so, this
could be the struggle in the heavens.
Dante will have to struggle with himself
in order to let go of his ego and his
fears to truly understand the meaning of
God, okay? And Beatrice will be his
guide in this, okay? So, we've
established our three Dantes. And it's
really important question to understand
that Dante the poet, Dante the real
person, and Dante the uh pilgrim.
Who is speaking now?
Who's the person speaking?
Who says, "Oh good Apollo, for this
final task, make me the vessel of your
excellence." Who's speaking?
The poet, right? That's protagonist. The
poet.
All right?
So, what's happening is
that this journey that Dante went on in
the heavens,
this is
a long time ago.
And Dante Apollo is sitting at home
where he is, he's he's actually in
exile, he's trying to remember and write
down what he experienced 20 years ago.
Okay, does that make sense?
And what he's saying is that what he
experienced 20 years ago was so
beautiful,
so beyond our comprehension, that he's
lost the memory of what happened 20
years ago.
And so now he has to reconstruct,
re-imagine
the experience.
And to do that, he calls upon not only
Apollo, but all the muses
who
um live on the two mountains of
Parnassus, of Parnassus, right? So, not
just Apollo, but every possible source
of inspiration he will call upon, he
will invoke in order to truly remember
what he experienced 20 years ago. Okay,
does that make sense?
What's the paradox here?
There's a paradox in all of this. What
is this?
>> Is this Christian?
>> Yeah, guys, this is a Christian
text meant for Christians. This is a
Catholic world, the Catholic Church is
in charge, and he's calling upon Apollo.
Right?
Why is he doing this?
What's he saying here?
Yeah?
>> So, um
this just reminds me of the text of
Gregory of Tours,
who is actually a monk. Like, he's
literally part of the church, and before
he
wrote about King Alfred, he wrote in the
preface, "Oh, Apollo, help me to write
King Lear very well." So,
first off, maybe this is like generally
accepted within the current social
atmosphere to invoke Apollo as an author
to ask him to make your writing really
good.
>> Okay, all right. So, you you just made a
statement. Maybe this is just accepted
at this time.
Well, we know for a fact it's not
accepted at this time. Um Carol, could
could could could could you go to
Google, please?
>> Sure.
>> And what what what what what we're going
to do is we're going to Google
uh medieval Christian art, okay?
We're going to Google medieval Christian
art.
And
we're just going to show images, okay?
When you see the images, it's pretty
consistent, okay? Can you go to images?
Yes. Okay, guys, can you see the images?
There are lots and lots of images. This
This is all Christian art.
What do you not see?
>> You don't see Jesus.
>> You don't see the common man.
>> Exactly, okay? You don't see any man.
These are all saints or religious
figures in the Bible, okay? That's point
one. There is no common man in any of
this.
What's number two? What what what what
what's another sharp difference?
These are Christian figures, right?
There's no paganism in any of these
paintings. You don't have Greek gods.
You don't have Apollo anywhere. Keep on
looking. This It doesn't exist. Why?
Because the church banned these things.
Right?
Okay?
So, yes, um
um there are Christians who do invoke
Apollo, but it's not a common thing.
It's It's banned by the
uh church, okay? So, um one thing to
keep in mind is that throughout history,
elite education is very different from
popular art, okay? What the elite study
at university is going to be very
different from what you see in popular
culture.
Um and so
the way they reconcile this is that at
this time in history, this this this
year 1321 when Dante
uh is
publishing The Divine Comedy or
making it public
um the elite learn Latin. And Latin is a
secret language of the elite, right? And
there you can like invoke Apollo and
like it doesn't really matter. And then
there is the vernacular, right? What
people experience in everyday life. And
that is heavily censored.
Now, what is revolutionary of The Divine
Comedy is that it is written not in
Latin, which is the language of the
elite, it's written in the vernacular,
in Tuscan.
Which is what every
ordinary person can read and access,
okay? So, this is a
The Divine Comedy is an act of rebellion
in in in many ways. It's It's an act of
revolution. If it was written in Latin,
this would not be a problem.
But it's it was written in the
vernacular.
Okay? And this is why
The Divine Comedy
will become the blueprint for not just
the Renaissance, Italian Renaissance,
but all of modernity itself.
Because the ideas in The Divine Comedy
become central
to modernity and the Renaissance.
The other thing that's really important
about art and public culture at this
time is
there are no protagonists. Or sorry, not
not the only type, but the common man is
not in the artwork. It's not in the
literature.
But, who's the main protagonist of
Divine Comedy? A common man, Dante.
Okay?
Individualism, individuality.
So, all these concepts we take for
granted today
were actually
uh revolutionary.
And it was Dante who would launch this
revolution, okay? So, this is not just a
poem, it's an intellectual revolution.
Okay, it's an act of courage, it's an
act of faith.
All right? So, uh
let's let's continue to read. Um
um Carol?
Enter into my do my breast.
>> Enter into my breast, within me breathe
the very power you made manifest
when you drew Marsyas out of his limbs'
sheath.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, good.
So, the thing about the about Divine
Comedy is that there are a lot of
illusions
in here, okay? So,
um
what Dante's going to do is he's going
to reference a lot of mythology
surrounding
uh
uh Apollo. So, Apollo
um had a competition with
another
uh
poet, Mar- Marsyas, and they basically
uh had a competition about who who would
be the better poet. And Marsyas lost,
and Apollo basically skinned him alive,
okay? It's It's a It's a pretty gruesome
story, but
um there's a lot of mythology being
driven being driven into here, okay? Uh
keep keep on going.
>> O godly force, if you so lend yourself
to me that I might show a shadow of the
blessed realm inscribed within my mind.
>> So, again, this is paradoxical, where he
is invoking Apollo in order to describe
a Christian heaven.
Okay?
I'm going.
>> Then you would see me underneath the
tree you love. There I shall take as
crown the leaves of which my theme and
you shall make me work.
>> What's the tree that Apollo loves? Do
you guys know?
>> Laurel.
>> The laurel tree, yes.
Can Can you Who said Who said that?
Okay. Can Can Can you Do you know the
legend here?
>> I impress the legend.
>> Yeah, so basically Apollo had a lover
and the lover
>> no, he didn't have a lover.
>> Oh.
>> Yeah, he had someone he loved, right?
>> Oh, yeah, yeah. He had Oh, yeah, right,
and then it became a lover for him. So,
uh he had someone he loved and uh that
person did not want to be his lover
>> Daphne Daphne is her name.
>> Yeah, and basically
uh
basically that person told was running
from Apollo because Apollo was chasing
her and that person told Athena
uh oh, please don't let Apollo be my
lover and Athena turned her into a
laurel tree and Apollo can no longer be
her lover.
>> Right, but Apollo loved her so much that
he also
um makes the laurel tree his symbol,
right? So, if you are a champion, a
poet, he gives you the laurel wreaths,
okay?
So,
um
not only is Dante invoking Apollo,
asking for his divine power, but he is
also
remembering or reciting the stories
that make Apollo famous, okay?
Um
What point is he trying to make here?
Why is he doing this?
Yes?
>> Um I wonder if he's trying to reinvent
heaven and the concept of paradise that
is not just a Christian paradise, but it
could also coexist with the Greek idea
of heaven and gods, maybe.
>> Right. Uh the problem though is that the
Greeks didn't have a concept of heaven,
right?
>> Yeah, there's Mount Olympus, but yeah,
not really.
>> The Greeks didn't have heaven.
So so what is he trying to do here?
So
what So for Dante,
um
he
is
trying to
think about what creativity is,
right? He's trying to think about what
knowledge is.
And for him, if you are truly to have
knowledge, if you're truly to exercise
your imagination,
what would you need to do?
And how would that be different from the
teachings of the Catholic Church at this
time in history?
Yeah?
>> Well, he gives me the impression of
someone who worships enlightenment
regardless of source. So he is seeking
the the truth, like regardless of
source. It could be Apollo, it could be
God, but he'll take whatever will show
him the truth.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's that's correct,
right? The idea is if you really want to
know the truth, you have to open-minded.
But not only do you have to be
open-minded, but you have to rigorously
draw on from different traditions, okay?
Because
these traditions exist for a reason, and
you need to combine these traditions in
in order to reach a truth. And guess
what, guys? This becomes the basic
premise of the Renaissance, right?
Okay? So, Carol, can we can we do a
Google search?
>> Sure.
>> Renaissance art. Okay?
So, we This is Christian art, right, you
guys? It's pretty static.
It's just
depictions of biblical passages, right?
But when you look at Renaissance art,
you see how vibrant
it is. It's drawing from different
traditions, okay? So,
can you show this?
Yeah.
Uh
maybe maybe in the uh
or the
Yeah, the School of Athens, okay? So,
this is one of the most famous
Renaissance paintings, the School of
Athens.
Okay. Uh
yes, I I I see you, Peter. But but but
but Okay, look, the School of Athens,
right?
It's drawing from
all possible traditions. You just look
at this painting, and we don't have time
to look at this painting, but there is
not just Christian thinkers, it's Muslim
thinkers, it's pagan thinkers, okay? And
the idea is implanted in the Divine
Comedy. This will not This painting
would not have been possible without
Dante, okay? It was Dante who basically
said, "If we are truly to know God, if
we are truly to discover the truth, we
must embrace all possible
religions,
all possible philosophies." Um
uh yes, did did did did did you have a
question?
Okay. Uh Peter, we have a question from
the livestream?
>> Uh so, livestream right now is not
working well.
>> Okay.
I mean, it's fine. We we we we we we
have the video camera, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, it's fine. What I mean, like yeah,
it's just in the Yeah. Okay, we'll we'll
continue, okay? All right. So, do you do
you see what's happening, okay?
We have now this radical leap from
Christian medieval art to Renaissance
art. You can see the vastness of the
difference. It's Dante that's doing
this, okay? Yes?
>> Um I remember going to Italy and then I
remember seeing the middle medieval art.
The babies look really scary because I
think uh the the church guy explained
that baby is supposed to be Jesus when
he was a baby, but when he was a baby he
was still this like divine figure, so
that's why they drew him like a
middle-aged man. But in Renaissance art,
they start drawing like baby faces and
real human proportions, like this idea
of individuality as you expressed
earlier. So, they started trying to see
humans as they really are rather than
what spiritually like religiously they
should represent.
>> Yeah, exactly. So, the major difference
between uh medieval art and Renaissance
art is that with medieval art, you're
trying to condition
the Christian in a certain mentality,
uh one of fear and humility.
To be always afraid, but also to
to be humble before God. Whereas
Renaissance, what and the Renaissance
becomes the
uh launching pad for modernity because
the Renaissance is trying to activate
the human imagination, okay? And so, the
way you do that is you make humans the
central character in the story of
humanity, okay? Uh and that's what's
happening in Dante where Dante makes
himself the central character. And this
is again unique at this time.
Um but also you're trying to show the
beauty and the power of the human
imagination, okay? All right.
All right. All right. Let's keep on uh
going.
Uh sorry, did did you did you have a
question?
>> Um no, I just have a comment about I
think he's quite advanced in his
theology that he believes if you want to
invoke the truth, you have to draw from
many sources. But the fact that it's
from Greek as well is kind of the same
as how Christianity started with Jesus
being born from Virgin Mary, which is a
very Greek kind of storyline. So maybe
he's trying to show his theology ideas
that Jesus in you know, like the
Christian God himself, you know, uses a
Greek traditional way to make him known
that he's a son of God.
>> Okay, all right. So a couple comments.
First of all, uh let's work with precise
terminology. He is not a theologian. He
is a poet. This is poetry, not theology,
okay? There's a lot of theology, there's
a lot of philosophy in this, but it's
poetry. This is a major difference,
okay? Theology is trying to explain
religion. Poetry is to activate the
imagination.
Okay, the religious imagination.
That's point one. Point two is
everything that you're saying is not
raw, but you're seeing it from the year
2026.
And this was written in the year 1321,
okay? And so back then, people would
just have a very different conception of
the universe.
Basically, uh at this point in history,
um the Catholic Church is trying to
create a Christian theology that is
self-contained.
Okay? That is distinct from all other
traditions and is in conflict with other
traditions, especially the Muslim
tradition,
which is at this point in history the
most powerful religious tradition in the
world, okay? So keep this in Keep this
in mind, guys. A lot of things you think
uh
it could be because you're looking at it
from a 2026 lens.
All right? But remember this year 1321.
Okay? So it's hard to do, but keep this
in the back of your mind, okay? All
right. Any more comments or questions
before I move on?
Okay, let's keep on going.
>> So seldom, Father, are those garlands
gathered for triumph of ruler or poet,
poet, a sign of fault or shame in human
wills that when the name branches can
incite someone to long and thirst for
them, the light must fill the happy
delphic deity.
>> So he's again talking to Apollo, right?
He's calling him Father, not capital F
Father, but Father, okay? So he is um um
invoking Apollo as a lesser god, which
is sacrilege, by the way, in in this
world, okay?
Uh keep on going.
>> Great fire can follow a small spark.
There may be better voices after me to
pray to Ser as God for aid.
>> Ser as God is Apollo.
Um
>> that he may answer.
The lantern of the world approaches
mortals by varied paths.
>> Lantern of the world is the sun, right?
Which is Apollo. And Apollo can reach
you through different paths. And he's
trying to invoke Apollo, right? He's
trying to reach Apollo. Keep on going.
>> But on that way which links four circles
with three crosses it emerges joined to
a better constellation
and along a better course and it can
temper and stamp the world's wax war in
its own manner.
>> Okay, so let's try to unpack what's
going on, okay? So he's saying he wants
to reach Apollo. He wants to
uh summon and invoke Apollo. And there
are many ways you can do that, but the
way that links four circles with three
crosses is the best way. Okay?
So now what what we're going to do is
we're going to try to figure out what
the four crosses with sorry four circles
and three crosses is. And by the way,
um everything that I am
saying is my own interpretation. Okay?
Um but I think that it's really
important to figure out what four
circles and three crosses are. Okay? So
you basically have
uh four circles and three crosses.
Four circles.
Three crosses.
All right. So and now what what what
what we're going to try to do is use
your imagination to figure out what this
thing is.
Okay?
All right. So
uh let's try to make it as simple as
simple as possible. Three crosses. What
are the three crosses?
Yes?
>> The Holy Trinity maybe?
Like the Trinity, God, and the Son and
the Father.
>> Um
Like the Trinity.
>> No, that's not that's that that's not
what the Trinity is.
Come on. The three crosses. It It's No
one here Christian? Yes?
>> I'm
I'm Christian. It's when Jesus died.
Like the
>> Yes! Yes! Do you understand? When Jesus
died, he died on the cross with two
other people, okay?
That's what the three crosses are. It's
Jesus, right? This is Jesus
on Mount Calvary.
Right? That's pretty obvious.
What are the four circles? This is
harder.
Yes?
>> Maybe the four elements?
Uh water, fire, earth, wind.
>> Yes, that is a possibility, but what are
the circles?
It's four, right? You There's four
elements, but what are the circles at?
>> [snorts]
>> When you think circle, what do you
think?
>> Spheres.
>> Spheres, right?
Planets, sun.
Right?
So four suns is what?
Call them the four seasons, right?
Okay?
Okay, so this is the um let me Okay, so
again, it's really important we figure
this out, okay?
The
four
equinoxes, right?
Okay, so you have the two equinoxes
as well as the two solstices.
And then that would be the four seasons.
Okay, so that's what these four circles
really are.
Then you have the three crosses.
And we And the three crosses we know are
uh Jesus.
What tradition cares a lot about the two
equinoxes and two solstices?
>> Pagan.
>> Exactly, the pagan tradition, okay?
So now we have a paradox.
What is a pagan tradition doing with a
Christian tradition? Christian tradition
is clearly the three crosses.
The four circles are clearly the pagan
tradition.
There's a paradox here.
Okay?
All right, so let's figure out this
paradox.
If you were to be transport transported
back 3,000 years into the pagan world,
okay?
Can somebody explain to me what the
pagan world is like and how you would be
you would feel I don't actually like
this place.
You would feel uncomfortable in the
pagan world. Why?
What makes the pagan world different
from our world? Yes?
>> Uh so I'm just to preface this, I'm
neo-pagan, so some of my idealizations
of paganism might be well, idealized.
But what I think is that uh paganism is
more primal and more varied. So we're
used to a Anglo-Christian world, we're
used to a homogeneous world, we're used
to people agreeing with our ideas, and
when they don't, we argue with them. But
uh the pagan world is
more almost more tolerant in in a way.
Like, there's more gods, there's more
opinions, and you're likely to run into
someone who won't agree with you.
>> Okay, so so this is confusing because
neo-paganism, the modern pagan world,
uh it embraces many different ancient
traditions, including Druidism, animism,
but
throughout most of human history, you're
pagan,
what idea, what thing were you most
concerned with?
What were you really concerned with as a
pagan? Yes?
>> That you don't upset the gods.
>> Why?
>> Well, because
Well,
you you can't not upset the gods.
>> Okay. How did you make your living?
What did you What What did you did What
did you do for a living?
>> Farming.
>> Farming, right?
>> If you upset upset the gods, they have a
drought or a huge rainstorm, and all of
your crops are gone.
>> Exactly, right? Would you be comfortable
in this world?
W- Why not?
Why would you be comfortable in this
world of
paganism? Yes?
>> Well, you constantly live in fear.
>> You constantly live in fear?
>> No, like if they
>> [clears throat]
>> if you're doing the right thing, you
know?
>> Yes.
Right? You have absolutely Yes?
>> Uh more essentially, I think it's the um
ambiguity. You have to be comfortable
with not knowing what the gods want to
do to you.
>> Right. So, yes?
>> And you can't predict the actions of
your fellow human beings as well as in a
Christian
>> You might have to turn it on.
>> Sorry.
Um turn this on.
>> You can't predict the actions of your
fellow human beings as well as you would
in a Christian conservative
>> Right.
So, the reality is that in the
pagan agricultural world, okay, where
the focus is on fertility, you have
absolutely no agency.
Right? You have no individuality.
>> [cough]
>> Life [clears throat] is passive for you,
okay? It's not about what you can do,
it's really about appeasing the gods.
Right? So, there's really no
individuality. It's really hard for you
to be
um creative or to make your mark on the
world. Right?
So, yes?
>> But, uh I have a question here. Like,
you just told us earlier that medieval
Christian art and even the Catholic
Church in Dante's time uh suppressed
creativity and promoted God-fearing
humility. So, how is that different?
>> Okay, that's a good question. So, we're
talking about medieval Christian Europe
in the year 1300, right?
But, this is referring to Jesus at the
time of his crucifixion, which is about
the year 33, around 33, okay?
All right?
What it Okay, you For the Christians in
this room, what why did Jesus have to
die? Why was his crucifixion, his death,
such a historical event? Why?
Yes?
>> Because there's no way for man himself
to atone for his sins, and man cannot um
be sinless, stainless, so to pay the
price for his actions.
>> So, what what was Jesus?
>> So, Jesus was the faultless lamb who can
die for human
>> no, what was Jesus?
>> Son of God.
>> Yes.
>> So, God himself has to come
>> of God, who is what?
>> Who is the Messiah?
Who is sinless.
>> Who is But, but, but is he a man or is
he not a man?
>> He's both. So is the father.
>> Exactly. You understand this, okay?
You understand this is important.
He is both son of God and he's a man as
well.
You understand?
Okay? And it it it
If you're not a Christian, it's kind of
weird, but for like 2,000 years they've
argued about this, all right? But if
Jesus If you want to understand
Christianity, you need to understand
that
Jesus was both a man
as well as a God.
And if you're a man, you're able to
redeem all humanity, now you have
agency.
Right?
Now you're able to mark a new period in
human history. So what's happened is
that
in the pagan world view, the universe is
a circle. It's a procession of
equinoxes, okay? It's an endless
seamless
uh cycle, okay? Like the like the
seasons. There's winter, which gives
rise to spring, which gives rise to
summer, then autumn, and so on and on
and on. There's nothing you can do about
it, okay? Okay? But with Jesus,
the circle now becomes a line.
Right? The circle becomes a line. So
when you put together the four circles
and the three crosses, you get a new
beginning of human history in which the
individual
matters now. Yes?
>> Yes.
But that was but the Catholic Church
wanted to suppress, right? Like this
this knowledge that you can free
yourself. So the Catholic Church said,
"No, you need us to
get to heaven."
>> Right. So exactly. So And this is what
Tony is saying. He's saying that the
Catholic Church and Jesus
and Christianity, these aren't
necessarily the same things, okay? All
right? So,
with this poetry, Dante is trying to
create a new understanding of
Christianity. And this is again this is
what gives rise to the Renaissance as
well as modernity. Okay, but does this
make sense to you? Okay? And what And
what he's doing that's really important
is he's creating paradoxes, right? What
is What is Why is paganism a symbol of
paganism, the four circles? Why is it
linked to the symbol of Christianity,
the the three crosses?
And the answer is because
for humanity to progress, you need both
traditions in place.
Okay?
Well, these traditions together, there
is no path to enlightenment. There is no
path to Apollo. This is the best path
possible.
Okay, does that make sense? Again, this
is my interpretation.
Poetry can only be interpreted. Okay?
And I'm sure there's been a lot of Dante
scholars who are very angry at me for
making this interpretation.
But I think this is a possible
interpretation that aligns with other
things that Dante will say throughout
the Divine Comedy, okay?
Are we clear? And yes?
>> So, uh
in summary, the idea is like the sun
shines on the world and it doesn't just
shine on Christians, it shines on
everyone.
>> That's what Dante believes, okay?
But what what What he's going to do
later on that is even more revolutionary
is say,
"It's not God's choice whether or not to
shine on you.
It's your choice
whether you want God to shine on you or
not."
Does that make sense to you?
All right?
Uh but this this this comes later.
All right. So, any more questions before
we move on?
Okay, let's let's continue.
Um
>> Its entry from that point of the upper
horizon brought morning there and
evening here.
>> So, he's talking about the sun, right?
>> Almost all of that hemisphere was white
while ours was dark.
When I stopped Beatrice turn around and
left that she might see the sun no eagle
has ever stared so steadily at it.
And as a second ray will issue from the
first and reascend
much like a pilgrim who seeks his home
again
so on her action
that by my eyes to my imagination
my action drew
and on the sun I set my sight more than
we usually do.
More is permitted to our powers there
than is permitted here
by virtue of that place made for mankind
as its true home.
I did not bear it long but not so
briefly as not to see it sparkling round
about
like molten iron emerging from the fire.
And suddenly it seemed that day had been
added to day as if the one who can had
graced the heavens with a second sun.
>> Okay.
>> The eyes of Beatrice were all intent on
the eternal circles. From the sun I
turned aside. I set my eyes on her.
And watching her within me I was changed
as Glaucus changed tasting the herb that
made him a companion of the other sea
gods.
>> Okay, so if there's something that's
really confusing about the by hominy is
that different universes are existing in
parallel with each other, right? So,
there is the universe of the Greeks,
right? Where Apollo is the sun. Now,
he's switching to the Christian universe
where God is the sun, okay? So, all
these universes are existing in parallel
with each other.
Um and the reason why is that we are in
heaven. We are in
uh paradise. And so, this is in the
spirit world.
Okay?
So, let me ask you this question.
It's a hard question, but think about
this.
Pretend you're a ghost or a spirit,
okay?
Can you
perceive time and space? Is it possible
for you to perceive time and space?
Yes?
>> No, because
I mean, you're immortal. Well, like you
live forever. Why would you perceive be
able to perceive time then?
I mean,
it wouldn't make sense. Well, it is like
spirits never die or they they've always
been there since
the universe existed.
>> Well, I understand, but you you still
keep time, right? Why can't you perceive
time and space? The answer is no, you
can't perceive time and space. There's a
really good reason why you cannot.
Yes, have you guys thought about this?
Yes?
>> Obviously, because you can't interact
with time and space. [clears throat]
Your soul is immune to the influences of
time and space. You don't have a body to
be uh battered
>> Yeah.
>> or otherwise.
>> Yeah, so the trick the key is to
understand that without a body, it's
impossible for you to understand time
and space, okay? And this is what
Immanuel Kant tells us.
What time and space is is space is
sensation. Sensation is made possible
for the five senses, okay?
Distance is between a body. If you don't
have a body, you wouldn't have a
conception of distance, okay?
And what time is time is sequence, which
is caused in the back.
Caused by sensation, right? I first had
this feeling and had that feeling.
That's time.
So, without a body, it's impossible for
you to experience time and space.
Okay? So, we are in a universe where
time and space don't exist. Everything
exists at once
and forever.
Okay? Different universes exist at the
same time. This is why all this is
possible.
And what Donnie is doing is he's using
words to decipher
this universe to make it comprehensible
to us because we are stuck in time and
space, but they are beyond time and
space. Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay?
Yes?
>> And how are these like spirits involved?
Are they like everywhere
like at the same time? Or like how are
these spirits involved in in humans? Or
like because
uh is it through emotions?
>> I I don't understand the question. Can
you repeat that?
>> Yeah, like these spirits, there's
there's multiple, right? So,
um and in the Greek world,
they
I mean, the Greek world used you would
say they they did have a body because,
you know, there's all these gods
that came down to Earth. So, they had to
like inhabit a body in the end.
>> But the Greek world in the Greek world,
what happened was these spirits took
possession.
You understand?
They didn't come to us as material
forms. They took possession of animals,
like Zeus,
or they took possession of people,
right?
>> But well, then then they were able to
perceive time and space.
>> That's right, but only they they can
take possession of your of someone's
body.
>> Okay.
>> Okay? Does that make sense? Right? So,
that's what Donnie is doing. He's trying
to have Apollo possess him so that he's
able to use the powers of Apollo, okay?
All right.
Uh, let's keep on going.
>> Passing beyond the human cannot be
worded. Let block it serve as simile
until grace grants you the experience.
Whether I only was the part of me that
you created last, you
governing the heavens know, it was your
light that raised me.
When that wheel which you make eternal
through the heavens longing for you drew
me with the harmony you temper and
distinguish,
the fire of the sun then seemed to me to
kindle so much of the sky that rain or
river never formed so broad a lake.
The
The newness of the sound and the great
light incited me to learn their cause. I
was more keen than I had ever been
before, and she who read me as I read
read myself to quiet the commotion in my
mind opened her lids before I opened
mine.
>> Okay, all right. So, do you guys
understand the sequence of events,
right? So, he starts off invoking Apollo
and says, "I had this great dream or
experience 20 years ago.
Please, Apollo, give me the power to
describe what I saw with words because
what I saw was beyond common space. It
is beyond the imagination
of
ordinary mortals, okay? Like like us,
the readers today, okay? And now what
he's doing is he's now describing as a
pilgrim his experience 20 years ago with
Beatrice.
Okay?
Keep on going.
>> Opened her lips before I opened mine to
ask, and she began,
"You make yourself accused with false
imagining.
You cannot see what you would see if you
dispelled it.
You're not on the Earth as you believe,
but lightning flying from its own abode
is less swift than you are returning
home."
>> Okay, so they are in the heavens, which
is beyond time and space. But, in order
for Dante to understand what's going on,
the universe has constructed the
universe in a way
for Dante to process. So, it's linear.
There is a bit of time and space, okay?
And what Beatrice is saying is saying to
her to him, basically, is
"Here, you have to completely rely on
your intuition and your imagination,
okay? Do not try to use logic. Do not
try to take what you learn in on Earth
and apply here. It will just confuse
you, okay? So, before you can meet God,
you have to go on this journey to dispel
your false imaginings, okay? Let go of
your ego, let go of your doubts, let go
of your fear so that you can truly
embrace God, yes?"
>> I don't know if this is going to be
talked about later, but is this kind of
also an allegory to Christianity?
Because um certain Christian apologists
have argued before
that uh obviously faith is what you need
to for for Christianity.
By using logic, that's where we can sort
of fall into sin.
>> Um he will address this later on, okay?
He will talk to Paul,
who is the person who says this, right?
For Paul, faith is
um
um to believe without uh without
evidence. Uh yeah, so talk about this
later on. Yes. Good.
All right.
Any more questions before we go on?
Are you guys following along? Because it
gets harder and harder, okay? Well
Yes?
>> I I have a quite innocent question. I
just feel curious like why there's no
need for logic in the heaven because it
seems like in order maybe for
communication in the world I think it's
necessary to have it anywhere, right?
Because
I mean if people don't do not use logic
or their like daily conversation, how
could that be? I mean any place.
>> Is there a How How about I answer this
question?
Yeah?
>> Uh so
you're in heaven. You're in spirit. Your
body's not there. You don't need to move
your teeth, move your meat crab to talk.
You can just
tele- tele-teleport around.
>> Yeah, I know. I mean I mean it doesn't
mean like you have to physically to make
a sound or vibrate, too. Like let others
to receive your message, but I mean
because like even if you are a spirit,
you still have your conscious, right? So
how could you guys like using that to
make your conscious have the agreements
even if you don't have you don't have to
use the logic.
>> Yeah, that's exac- that's exactly the
point. You You don't have to make people
agree with you. You can just think about
it and everyone will understand what
they what you mean.
>> Yes?
>> Oh, yeah. Because I think Bruce Lee has
just said that don't think, feel. So
maybe I think Bruce Lee is just like
kind of philosopher, right? Just said
just like even like that thing said
don't think, feel.
>> Okay. All right. So so so let me answer
your question, okay? Because this is a
question that most high school students
are going to have.
>> [laughter]
>> If you're in high school, logic does
matter because you have to take tests,
okay? But that's the point of logic, to
take tests and to pass tests and make
the teacher give you a good grade, okay?
Logic is a system we developed in order
to uh control the way you behave and
think in our world, okay? But our world
is a subset of the entire universe. And
quite honestly,
um
there are many issues with logic, okay?
So, for example,
um mathematics and science um really
constrain your capacity to perceive
the the world. And this is something
that will become much more clear as you
continue to read the Divine Comedy.
Okay?
All right.
Um but but but what Dante will say is
that
logic are like changed changed, okay? To
keep you
in a certain mindset. Imagination
is like a bird that can float around
everywhere. And so, to truly
understand
God, to truly understand the Divine
Comedy, you have you you your mind has
to become almost like a bird and just
fly around and follow your intuition.
Okay?
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> While I was freed from my first doubt by
these brief words, she smiled to me. I
was yet caught in new perplexity.
I said, "I was content already. After
such great wonder, I rested."
>> Okay, sorry sorry I'm sorry, okay, all
right. So, um what while I was freed
from my first thought doubt by these
brief words, she smiled to me. I was yet
caught in new perplexity, okay?
So, what is his first doubt?
>> Am I really here?
>> Okay.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, he is not
Anyone else?
What is this doubt?
It's really hot.
Am I really here? He's not sure where he
is,
right?
Okay.
And what he's just telling you and him
is that we are in a new universe that is
beyond time and space, okay? So,
if they're going to go visit the moon
and Venus and the sun and Jupiter and
Saturn, these are not our Jupiter or our
Saturn, okay?
Okay, these are metaphor metaphors. This
is another universe, okay? That's his
first um
doubt, okay?
But once you have this first doubt, what
other questions might you have?
>> Okay.
Can I stay?
>> To me?
>> Uh can I stay?
>> Can I stay?
>> Do I belong here?
>> To me?
>> Do I belong in this realm?
>> Yeah, how does this realm work?
Yeah?
>> How did I get up there?
>> Yeah, like it's like this first thing
like we're in a new universe
it raises all sorts of different
questions, okay?
And so, this is what makes
Dante
Dante's conception of the universe
unique because heaven it is not
perfection, it is not the end, it's just
another journey. It's just another place
for you to ask questions.
Okay, does that make sense?
All right? So,
um
yeah, okay. Uh can can you keep on
reading Carol?
>> Sure.
I said, I was content already after such
great wonder. I rested. But again, I
wonder how my body rises past these
lighter bodies.
>> Okay, so she's trying to figure out how
this universe works, right? Because
they're flying throughout the cosmos.
And he's like
why am I flying?
Right?
He's completely confused by what's going
on. But but again, what what's important
to understand is that there is no time
and space in this universe. Time and
space has construct has been constructed
for Dante's personal benefit so that he
can ex- so that he can he can understand
what's going on. All right? Does that
make sense? Okay, keep on going.
>> At which, after a sigh pity, she settled
her eyes on me with the same look a
mother casts upon a braiding child, and
she began.
All things among themselves possess an
order, and this order is the form that
makes the universe like God.
Here do the higher beings see the
imprint of the eternal work, which is
the end to which the pattern I have
mentioned tends.
Within that order, every nature has its
bent according to different station,
nearer or less near to its origin.
Therefore, these natures move to
different ports across the mighty sea of
being, each given the impulse that will
bear it on.
This impulse carries fire to the moon.
This is the motive force in mortal
creatures.
This binds the earth together, makes it
one.
Not only does the shaft shot from this
bow strike creatures lacking intellect,
but those who have intelligence and who
can love.
>> Okay, so so what what she's saying here
is that
God created the universe in a certain
structure, okay? And God permeates the
entire universe and touches us all,
okay? And there is a logic, a reason, a
coherence
to the universe. What Dante's going to
do is try to figure out what this logic
is. What is the
organizing principle of the universe?
Why has God constructed the world the
way he has, okay?
You want to go ahead. And even this is
it should even happen, okay? So, there's
there's a hierarchy even in heaven. Go
ahead and go ahead.
>> The providence that has arrayed all this
for or requires
with its light that heaven in which the
swiftest of the spheres revolves.
To there, as toward a destined place, we
now are carried by the power of the bow
that always aims its shaft at a glad
mark.
Yet it is true that even as a shape may
often not accord with art's intent,
since matter may be unresponsive, deaf,
so from this course the creature strays
at times because he has the power, once
impelled, to swerve elsewhere. As
lightning from a cloud is seen to fall,
so does the first impulse, when man has
been diverted by false pleasure, turn
him toward earth.
You should, if I am right, not feel more
marvel at your climbing than you would
were you considering a stream that from
a mountain's height falls to its base.
It would be cause for wonder in you if,
no longer hindered, you remained below,
as if on earth a living flame stood
still.
Then she again she again turned her gaze
heavenward.
>> Okay. So, here she's trying to explain
how the universe works, how it moves,
okay? Can someone, in simple terms,
explain to me what he's saying here?
You decipher, interpret what she's
saying here.
Yes.
>> Uh God assigned you a bunch of weights.
If you're light, you go up. If you're
heavy, you go down. If you're light and
you're still down, then you should be
worried.
>> Incorrect.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, good guess, though. That's not
That's not That's not what she's saying
at all.
Uh what what What do you think the
problem with this would be?
Why would Dante take objection to this
idea? You said that God assigns weights,
right?
Why would Dante be angry at all this
idea?
>> Uh technically, he's a human. However,
right here, he is like on the doorstep
of heaven. So, how did he get there?
>> Okay. So, let's first try to unpack this
idea. God assigns weights, okay? And
there are lots of Christians who do
believe this.
Okay?
Uh this is something that John Calvin
would argue.
But
Dante would find this really
objectionable. He'd be very angry at
this idea. Why?
>> Very judgemental.
>> Exactly. It's unjust. Do you understand?
Like, how can you justify giving someone
a heavy weight and someone a light
weight? Why would God do that? What's
the rationale for that?
>> And there's also a mention of natures
and many forms of natures. So,
multiple standards, multiple
perspectives.
>> Exactly, okay? So, God shines
everywhere, okay? And God would never be
judgemental. That goes against the
nature of God.
Okay? So, God is not is not judgemental.
God is all forgiving, all generous.
So that can't possibly be the answer
that God has assigned weights.
So what's what's another explanation?
Yes?
>> But if he did assign weights and if he
isn't judgemental, then how are some
people in heaven and some people are in
inferno?
>> Yeah, exactly. Right, that's what I'm
asking you. Yes?
>> Or is it we give ourselves the weights?
>> Exactly. Can you explain that?
>> Um cuz we have see through this
conception we have free will, so
yeah, if we if we obviously end up with
the heavy weights is because we've done
the greatest sin.
>> What is God Yes? Yes?
>> Well, also
what some religious people teach is just
that we can't forgive ourselves. So
we're not able to
like but we have
we could forgive ourselves, but some
people are
sinned so great that they're not in the
they don't have the power to forgive
themselves. So they think they don't
have the power.
>> Good. Okay, all right. So what is God
doing?
What is God What What is God what?
What is God doing? Pe- Pe- Pe- just tell
us explicitly what God is doing. What's
God doing?
>> action plan
>> What is God's action?
What What is God trying to do?
Yes?
>> So if the weights are the ones you put
on yourselves, then God is trying to
tell you to take them off yourself.
>> Okay. So what did you say? It's like God
is trying to draw you to him. You
understand?
Right? He's He He He's He's like
attracted to you, right? He's He's
locked you on. He's going to draw you to
him.
Okay? That's what God is trying to do.
But and like
what are you doing?
>> I imagine God's like a She She's like
watching a movie, right? He's sitting
back and watching everybody on their own
free will, navigating and exploring
their different perspectives of their
different uh
views of of of of things and as they
kind of go towards him or away from
>> Is God watching me?
Yeah.
What would God they say God is not
watching you?
But but I say God just keep watching all
of us. Yes, I say this kind of
confession and uh if you think you're
guilty then you you you have a thought
of God is there. For example, if you
steal steal something and you think it's
okay, nobody watch it, but your guilty
is still there. So, if your guilty is
still there it means that God is there.
So, maybe this what I what I thought.
Yes.
Again, is it more on agency or we
watching God or is he watching us?
Okay, can you explain that?
>> Um
It's more like obviously when when we
decide within ourselves if we want
salvation or we want to not seem to do
the right thing, we will look to God.
It's not that he's sort of watching us.
>> Exactly. So, so the the key is this, God
is always welcoming you, okay? God is
always trying to draw you to him.
But
because of the law of free will, of free
choice, it's entirely your choice what
to do.
You could welcome God, embrace God, and
then move towards
the light, which is what Donnie is
doing.
But you can also turn away from God
um and do what you want.
Okay? And this is how the universe
works.
And this is the basic premise you have
to work with.
Like everything you do is entirely
because you choose to do it.
Even though you may not think it's your
choice.
Okay? This is the fundamental law of the
universe. It's everything is free
choice. So, God doesn't exactly watch
you.
God's going to welcome you, but it's
going to be your choice whether or not
to move towards God
through your actions.
Okay? Through your desire and will. Does
that make sense?
Okay. And this is the premise
that Peters is going to elaborate on um
and extend on as they move across the
heavens. To to let God understand
and you, too. This means you choose to
do it. And why would God give you free
choice?
And why is God doing this?
Why is free choice, free will, the
ultimate law of the universe? Why has
God constructed the universe in such a
way?
Yes?
>> Because that way you're willingly loving
him or like following his his rules or
stuff. So, that you're not forced to
enter heaven or forced to
obey God's commands.
>> Okay. Okay, yes, that is true. But, I'm
saying like why does God give you free
will?
>> In the very physics imagination of it's
God as if you imagine God as energy and
God
energy tends to accumulate, tends to
want more of it. So, so as as you have
free will, all these agents having free
will gravitate towards that source of
energy, that source of energy becomes
larger.
Does that make sense?
>> I don't I think it makes sense, but I'm
not Yes.
>> Is it kind of cuz God doesn't have his
own free will, so he
uses through us?
>> Uh God doesn't have free will. That that
that doesn't make any sense. He's God,
right?
>> Like he he can't sit
>> Yes?
>> Uh I think it's it's exactly because God
is omnipotent. He can do everything he
wants, but he chooses to
uh give the freedom choice to people to
see
>> But why?
>> Just to see what people react.
>> Like an experiment?
>> [laughter]
>> Well,
>> He's experimenting on us.
Well, we're we're like like mice in a in
a lab, right? Yes? Yes?
>> Uh I think he wants humans to reach him,
so he would need a way for people to not
reach him to make a contrast for
people
uh making their journey like closer and
closer to him.
>> This sounds like like like a mice
experiment, right? You have this like
maze and you want the mouse to come to
you, right? Is that what God is doing?
Yes?
>> I mean, because God made man in his own
image and he wanted man to have agency
just like him.
>> But why does God want man to have
agency? Yes?
>> Uh because there's no good if there's no
evil.
Like like if
if they are willing to do good, there
[clears throat] there's actually good.
>> Okay, so again, God wants to create
good, so he has to create evil as well.
He says all of this is an experiment,
right?
And you have to you have to ask
yourself, would God actually do any of
this?
Yes?
>> Uh this is a bit of a radical opinion,
but what if God just didn't create us?
>> Then he's not God.
>> No, like what if we're independent from
him?
>> Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> Um this is Okay, but yes yes yes.
>> Um he doesn't want blind obedience from
humanity because if we are all forced to
believe in him, then he wouldn't be God
anymore.
>> Okay. Uh yes?
>> Um in the passage, uh
Dante writes, "Everything has a order."
All right?
>> That's right.
>> So, you know, rocks fall downward, the
fire burns upwards. So, it seems like
those things don't really have free
will, but as humans we can stray from
the path
and like
Whatever you like. So, so as humans like
we can we don't we don't automatically
have that order.
>> Okay. No, okay. So, we know there's free
will, okay? We know what makes us
basically human is our free will.
What I'm saying, why do we have this?
Why did God give us this? Yes?
>> Cuz God is actually within us.
So, he wants to experience it.
>> God is within us, so he wants to
experience
free will. But, God already has free
will.
God is God. God God can do whatever he
wants. In the in the material world.
In the material world.
Huh.
Does God care? Yeah, you can keep on
going.
>> Well, I would just say rather than we
can experiment, I would like to say that
God would like to have role like much
more like a charger because if people
have the free will, they won't do do
this stuff, follow their true heart by
their true meaning. So, that means there
will no camouflage that can make someone
feel
confused. Then the God can make the real
judgment based on people's action and
their true thoughts.
>> Okay. All right, so guys, again,
this is a problem because you're
overthinking this. It's not that hard.
>> That's what we do.
>> Here
you were a child, okay?
>> [clears throat]
>> How do you know
your parents truly love you? What is
that one
signal that your parents truly love you
unconditionally? What is it?
>> You can do whatever you want.
>> Exactly.
Free will. You understand?
>> What what How about I just kind of like
the judge in in the law is called
the motivation.
>> a judge, okay?
>> It's kind of motivation like maybe
>> No, no, no. Okay.
God is perfection. God is the creator,
right?
God and God, to show he loves everything
in the universe,
gives freedom to the universe. Free
will.
Does that make sense?
Okay? And again, just think about your
parents. Just think about how if you're
a parent, how you treat your child. How
do you know you truly Your parents truly
love you? Because your parents support
you unconditionally.
You understand? That's what God is.
God loves you unconditionally. God would
never, ever ask you to anything.
God will not ask you to do good. God
will not ask you to do evil.
Okay? God will not ask you to aspire to
him.
Free will is the ultimate law of the
universe because
that is how God expresses his love to
you. God exists to love you.
Does that make sense?
>> Uh well, uh I don't I don't know, but uh
you know, I'm I'm also a father and I I
think my son I can't just give them
unconditional love because if I think
it's conditional love, it is you don't
take responsibility for him. For
example, if he's not my son, he can do
everything what what he want. I don't
care. But if he is my son, I have to
tell [laughter] him
All right, you're my son. You have to I
DON'T HAVE TO
>> THIS is
>> Okay, I don't want to turn it a debate.
We're trying to rewrite comedy. We're
trying to understand
what Quentin is saying here. Yes?
>> I kind of
hold the same opinion where it's like
Yeah, I agree with the idea that if
someone loves you, they will support you
unconditionally. And if you want to do
something, they will support that. But I
don't think it's given it's the same
thing as free will because the free will
is saying if I don't want to go to
sleep, my parents just won't let me go
to just let me stay up all night. And if
I don't want to eat my vegetables, my
parents let me eat candy. Like that
doesn't seem like like uh
uh them showing that they love you.
So like I don't think that
that free will necessarily is the same
thing as you know being supportive no
matter what.
>> What?
>> Yeah, and and there but like you
understand there are rules to the
universe, okay? For example, we don't
have the power to like blow up the
entire universe. Do you understand?
There are limits to what we can do. God
does have limits to us. Does that make
sense?
Okay? Uh yes?
>> So maybe I want to hold maybe I want to
pose a question at the very least.
Um it seems like
Eve ate
the apple from the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil.
And prior to that Adam and Eve didn't
have knowledge of this good and evil
which
perhaps would
negate
a bit of this free free will without
understanding
the dichotomy.
And
so perhaps you could say either
humans took for themselves
this free will
or that they were deceived. And they
were forced upon them by the serpent or
the devil or whoever you want to say.
And were forced this free will.
Does that seem to fit it all here?
>> Um
okay.
So
uh yes?
>> But the the fact that the tree existed
in the garden in the first place already
shows that God has given free will from
the beginning. So he has like you know a
a recommendation. I I recommend you not
to eat this fruit, but if you want it's
there, you know, like so from the very
beginning there is free will. It's not
like humans seek free will, got the
fruit, and then got free will, but it's
like
it's there.
>> Yeah, so so I mean
we'll get to the garden, okay? But
um
there are like so many ways you you can
understand what happened, okay? But like
what Dante will say is that
um
exactly that, which is if if God didn't
want us to
um
didn't want us the opportunity to
exercise our free will, he would not
have put the tree there in the first
place. And he would not have said, "Hey,
that's that tree. Don't touch it, okay?"
I mean yeah?
Uh
did you have a comment, yes?
>> Oh, well, this is a bit of a meta
narrative, but what what if God is
perfection, God is everything good, God
loves us, so no matter what God does to
us, that's a form of his love. If he
gives us free will, that's his love. If
he doesn't, that's his love. If he did,
then we can only assume that he loves
us.
>> Okay. All right. So, um
let me clarify something, okay?
This
Dante is beyond time and space.
Do you understand?
So, we cannot use our logic, we cannot
use our language to explain what's going
on.
But Dante is trying to use our logic,
our language to explain to us what's
going on.
Okay? So, this is not a literal
explanation. Oh, God is this force that
loves us. It's a metaphorical
explanation that helps us understand our
place in the universe. Does that make
sense? If you want to really go
into literal, then go study quantum
mechanics, right? How the universe is
entirely energy, vibrations, quantum
fields.
But but the question then for Dante is
like what does this mean, right? If the
universe is entirely energy, how does
this energy flow work?
And what does does mean for us? And what
Dante is trying to do is he's trying to
explain to us
what our place is
metaphorically, poetically. Does that
make sense? And the best way to
understand God is that God is this force
that loves us unconditionally and calls
us back to him, which is what will
enable us to be happy. But it's entirely
our choice whether or not to go to him.
He's trying to explain to us why we make
certain choices that we do. Okay, do you
understand? So this is poetry. This is a
metaphor. This is not quantum mechanics.
Does it make sense, guys?
All right. Any more questions be- be-
before we move on?
Okay. So I'm trying to establish the
major themes
that we'll be exploring throughout the
Divine Comedy, okay?
All right. Are we all clear?
All right. Let's let's let's move on to
Canto 2, please.
>> [clears throat]
>> And then start.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Oh, you or within your little bark,
eager to listen, following behind my
ship that singing crosses to deep seas,
turn back to see your shores again. Do
not attempt to sail the seas I sail,
you may, by losing sight of me, be left
astray.
>> Okay. So now he's talking directly to
us, the reader, right? He's the poet.
He's talking to us, the the the reader.
Keep on going.
>> The waves I take were never sailed
before.
Minerva breathes, Apollo pilots me, and
the nine Muses show to me the way.
>> Okay. So again, he's invoking all
possible inspirations
to help him through this process, okay?
And no one's ever been on this journey
before. And quite honestly, no one else
will be at whatever going on this
journey again.
And he kept on going.
>> You other few who turned your minds and
time unto the bread of angels, which
provides men here with life, but
hungering for more, you may indeed
commit your vessel to the deep salt sea,
keeping your course within my wake,
ahead of where waves smooth again.
Those men of glory, those who crossed to
Colchis, where they saw Jason turn into
a plowman, were less amazed than you
will be amazed.
>> So again, he's referencing Greek
mythology, Jason and the Argonauts,
okay? Keep on going.
>> The thirst that is innate and
everlasting
first for the godly realm bore us the
way as swiftly as the heavens that you
seek.
>> Okay. So, what he's saying is that our
fundamental hunger, our fundamental
need, our thirst, is to return to God.
And he feels God is close to him, so he
is moving really
uh quickly towards him.
>> Beatrice gazed upward. I watched her,
but in a span perhaps no longer than an
arrow takes to strike, to fly, to leave
the bow, I reached a place where I could
see that something wonderful drew me,
and she from whom my need could not be
hidden turned to me. Her gladness
matched her loveliness.
"Direct your mind to God in
gratefulness," she said. "He has brought
us to the first star."
>> Okay. So again,
um
heaven is divided into a hierarchy,
okay? Different
uh planes. The first plane is the moon,
okay? So they are on the moon right now.
>> It seemed to to that we were covered by
a brilliant, solid, dense, and stainless
cloud, much like a diamond that the sun
has struck. Into itself, the everlasting
pearl received us, just as water will
accept a ray of light and yet remain
intact.
If I was body, and on Earth we cannot
see how things material can share one
space, the case when body enters body,
then should our longing be still more
inflamed to see that essence in which we
discern how God and human nature were
made one.
What we hold here by faith shall there
be seen, not demonstrated but directly
known, even as the first truth that man
believes.
I answered with the most devotion I can
summon,
I thank him who has brought me far from
the mortal world. But now tell me, what
are the dark marks on this planet's body
that there below on Earth have made men
tell the tale of Cain?
>> Okay, so
they're on the moon, okay?
And Dante has a question, which is
why are there
dark spots on the moon? Actually, uh
Carol, could you um could we just like
Google the moon?
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. So, you guys have looked at the
moon, right?
You like dark spots on the moon and and
like you're like, "What are they doing
there?" Right? Like you have you guys
have seen the moon, right? It's like
Does anyone know why there are dark
spots on the moon?
>> Because there's craters from meteoroids.
>> Yeah, that's the standard explanation,
okay?
Um
the standard explanation is that there
are some craters and these craters have
certain material
that is not reflective. They absorb the
light. Okay?
All right? But
Dante's asking this question. Like my
first question is, "Why are there dark
spots on the moon?" And he said he's
going to have then and he's asking like
why the dogs watch on the moon. And so
for him it's a scientific journey,
right?
Okay, all right.
Keep keep keep on going, Carol.
>> She smiled somewhat, and then she said,
"If the opinion mortals hold falls into
error when the senses key cannot unlock
the truth, you should not be struck by
the arrows of the mind. But once you
recognize that reason, even when
supported by the senses, has short
wings."
>> Okay, so here she's saying, "Okay,
reason, logic don't work in the
universe. Okay, there is severe
limitations to science, to logic, to
reason."
All right? And so now we're forced to
use our intuition and our imagination.
If you truly believe in science, it's
going to only carry you so far.
Okay, you keep you keep on going, uh
>> Sorry. I'm back on practice.
>> I think imagination and intuition and
reason is all the
on same level or
transcendental cognitive faculties. So
why imagination or intuition is higher
than reason?
>> Okay, that's a good question. Okay, all
right.
So let's figure this out.
Reason and imagination are not the same
thing, okay? Logic, intuition are not
the same thing. Before I answer, does
anyone want to try? What's the
difference?
>> [clears throat]
>> You guys talk about this. What's the
difference between reason and
imagination?
>> I don't know. I'm going to try, but I'm
I might be very wrong. But I think that
like logic is more like about rational,
while imagination can be like very
irrational.
Like um
Yeah, like it can for example uh
different people will have
different
>> Yes.
>> Uh
yeah, I would say
logic it's
um the people in the past like what
their experience and summarize and
put into theory or you can say logic is
when is what people think when they're
in a
uh, normal state of mind and when they
go crazy or when they
just something happened to their brain
and they're thinking something else,
they that's
they can be more imaginative this way,
probably.
>> Yes.
>> I think to an extent, uh, logic and
reason, they try to explain the material
world, but when we go into the realm of
intuition and imagination, we can go
beyond the constraints of the material
world and just like do whatever we want
and kind of like
it's like the human the human nature, we
want to experience things that are
greater than this world that we live in.
So, that's why we sometimes we are drawn
to poetry writing.
>> Okay.
Okay.
All right, intuitively, I think, uh, the
difference between intuition and, uh,
logic and that
logic is, uh,
you know, it's like human being have a
multiplex
of, uh,
ways of thinking or,
uh, you know, um, experiencing the
universe, but logic is, uh, the
conscious human effort involving
language and other,
uh, you know, centralized method to
experience universe, whereas, uh,
uh,
intuition is, uh, invoking
the whole physical or mental capacity
without even being conscious.
>> Okay. All right. So, this is hard, okay?
But I I need you to understand the
difference between reason and
imagination, okay? The subtle difference
is this. With reason, what you're really
doing is dividing things into
categories. Does that make sense? In
order for you to reason, you have to
categorize something. For example,
you're a girl, you're a boy, girl, boy,
okay? And then from that, once I have
these categories, I can start to
reason things out, okay?
But the
But the But the But the categorization
is problematic because
like by categorizing, what I'm doing is
I am reducing.
I'm subtracting. I'm simplifying, okay?
Imagination is different because
imagination is about synthesis. It's
about adding, okay? So, you don't have
this categorizing process. You can take
leaps.
Okay? You can build things on top of
each other. So, that's what Nietzsche is
saying here. If you try to categorize
things, you're going to run into
problems because categorization by
itself is problematic. Does that make
sense?
Okay? You're try If you're trying to
reason out why the moon has dark spots,
right? You're like, "The moon is a
planet." Uh the planet You I Well, I
mean, do you do you understand what's
going on? Okay? You're trying to put
things into categories. And as a result,
it's going to confuse you.
All right, yes?
>> Is it also like if you use logic, you
can come up with many answers to one
question. But if you have intuition or
imagination, there's one truth.
Gut feeling.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's what I was going to
say. Like intuition is probably your
best guide.
Okay?
Uh any any any more? Yes?
>> Uh yeah, maybe I think this like, you
know, in ancient China, uh people did
just not believe in logic. They just
believe in the for example like uh
ancient or we can call love or
something. So, you have to show love to
your mother. You have to show love to
your master. You can't ask keep asking
question why I show love or what it can
give me return. But reason is different.
You have to get something in return.
Like, you know, why I love you? Because
I I I I need you, right? Why I need you?
Because you can give me something that I
need, right? So, I think maybe that is
difference.
>> Okay. So, [clears throat]
um
So, categorization is important because
categorization allows you to
better manipulate the material world.
Okay, does that make sense, guys? What
you able able to categorize means you're
also able to break things down to its uh
uh
basic elements and then manipulate them
to create technology. Okay, does that
make sense? But, there's a limitation to
this. And then the imagination is what
carries you through to the um deep
secrets of the universe. Okay, and that
and that's what Vision is saying here.
Okay, you are looking at the moon from a
logical, rational, scientific
perspective, and that will not let you
see the truth. Okay? The heart
and imagination will let you see the
truth. Okay, can you can you can you can
you can you continue, please?
>> Sure.
But, tell me what you think of it
yourself.
And I, what seems to us diverse up here
is caused, I think, by matter dense and
rare.
>> Okay, right. What's his explanation for
this?
It's a very simple explanation.
Why are the dark spots dark spots on the
moon?
Matters
dense and rare. What what what does he
mean by this?
>> Different density.
>> Can you can you explain, please?
Like like if you're just trying to
figure this out logically, what's the
most logical explanation why for why
there are dark spots on the moon?
>> Uh they're different materials. Or
craters from asteroids.
>> You know, that's not the most logical
explanation.
What is the most logical explanation?
>> Dirt has different colors.
>> No.
Guys, why are there dark spots on the
moon? Why is it that some parts reflect
and some parts don't reflect. Why?
>> I'll use the analogy.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh it would be cuz like it creates depth
and so the more far away the darker.
Like same as a cave would be.
>> Yeah.
Right. Okay. So, what we assume is that
there's certain parts of one that are
hollow.
Does that make sense? Like just from
large perspective like well, the parts
of one that are hollow and that's where
all the light just passes through,
right?
And there's some parts of one that is
pretty dense and so the light reflects
back. I'm just saying from a large
perspective when you use categorization,
right?
And analysis, you get to this
conclusion.
Okay?
If something is hollow,
it does not reflect light.
If something is not hollow,
light bounces back. Okay? We're just
using logic here.
And that's what Donny's saying.
It doesn't make sense.
Okay. Keep Keep Keep my way.
>> And she,
you certainly will see that your belief
is deeply sunk in error if you listen
carefully as I rebutted.
>> What What is really
interesting about the light company is
they're in heaven and they're having a
scientific debate, okay? They're having
a argument about the nature of science.
Keep my way.
>> The eighth sphere offers many lights to
you and you can tell that they in
quality and size are stars with
different visages.
If rarity and density alone caused this,
then all the stars would share one power
distributed in lesser, greater, or equal
force.
But different powers must be fruits of
different formal principles. Were you
correct, one only would be left, the
rest destroyed. And more,
>> Please stop. Okay, right. So, what she's
saying here is, okay, we are looking at
the heavens. The different stars have
different lighting, okay?
And she's saying like
if we can just reduce everything to
logic then this logic controls the
universe. And therefore, the entire
stars are lit
by this logic. Okay?
Um
but
she's going to tell us that can't be
true.
Okay, there's another force
that's at work.
Keep on going.
>> And more, were rarity the cause of the
dim spots to question, then in part this
planet would lack matter through and
through.
Or else as in a body, lean and fat can
alternate, so would this planet
alternate the pages in its volume.
>> Okay, so what she's saying is this,
okay? If it is true
that density is what determines
light
then what you're saying is there are
parts of the moon that are hollow.
[snorts]
Or
they have a deep cavity.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Okay?
Either possibility. Either First the
possibility that they're hollow or
there's a deep cavity inside the moon so
the light just goes into it.
Okay? Only one of these two
possibilities. And now what she's going
to do is she's going to refute both of
these arguments. Keep on going.
>> And more
Oops, I hear. And more, were rarity the
cause of the dim spots
I'm counting.
I will I'll just
>> Okay.
>> read it. And more, were rarity the cause
of the dim spots to question, then in
part this planet would lack matter
through and through. Or else as in a
body lean and fat can can alternate, so
with this planet alternate the pages in
its volume. To validate the first case
in the sun's eclipse, the light would
have to show through just as when it
crosses matter that is slender. This is
not so, therefore we must consider the
latter case. If I annulled that too,
then your opinion surely is confuted.
>> Okay, so she's saying
it's not possible for the moon to be
hollow at any point. Why?
It's not possible for the moon to be uh
Because
>> So the structure of the moon is not
>> Yes.
So anyone?
>> There's an eclipse in
>> The eclipse, right? You have You guys
have heard of the eclipse.
Right?
So it's not possible for the moon to be
hollow at any point, otherwise you
wouldn't have a eclipse, okay?
>> [clears throat]
>> Keep going.
>> If rarity does not run through and
through the moon, then there must be a
limit where thickness does not allow the
light to pass. From there, the rays of
sun would be thrown back just as from
glass that hides lead at its back, a ray
of colored light returns reflected.
Now you will say that where a ray has
been reflected from a section farther
back, that ray will show itself to be
more dim.
>> Okay, so so wait, that's that's the
logical argument, right? Well, maybe
the moon is not is not completely
hollow, but there are parts that are so
deep the light just is trapped, okay?
Keep going.
>> Yeah, an experiment where you're to try
it could free you from your cavil, and
the source of your art's course springs
from experiment.
>> Okay.
What is she saying here? She's saying
like, if you don't believe me and I'm
virtuous,
>> [clears throat]
>> I
am a representative of God. If you don't
believe me, what should you do?
>> Do an experiment.
>> Do it for yourself, man.
Do you understand? You don't have to
believe me. I am not forcing you to
believe anything. You have the power to
know the truth for yourself.
Okay? Do an experiment.
You know what I'm saying?
>> Taking three mirrors, place a pair of
them at equal distance from you. Set the
third midway between those two, but
farther back. Then, turning towards
them, at your back, have placed a light
that kindles those three mirrors and
returns to you reflected by them all.
Although the image in the farthest glass
will be of lesser size, there you will
see that it must match the brightness of
the rest.
>> Okay, so do you guys do you guys
understand the experiment? Okay? What
I'm doing is
I am putting mirrors in front of me,
okay? Maybe 10,000 from me, and I'm
putting it like a mirror
10,000 km away.
And I'm shining a
light at both, okay? Would the
brightness
differ
between these two
mirrors?
Yes or no?
No, it's the same brightness, okay?
And that 10,000 km mirror might be like
you can't actually see it, but if you
actually go there, it would just be as
bright. Okay? And this is an experiment
you can you can actually do at home.
You don't have to believe me. You can
just go home and try this experiment. No
matter how far it is from you, it will
still be as bright.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Right? So, it's not possible
for the cavity theory to be true as
well. So, through logic, through reason,
she's able to refute your logic and
reason as well.
So, this is a science debate.
Go on, go ahead.
>> Now, just as the soft matter of the snow
beneath the blows of the warm rays is
stripped of both its former color and
its cold,
so is your mind left bare of error.
I would off couch you a new form, light
so living that it trembles in your
sight.
>> Why is Beatrice wasting everyone's time?
Why is she doing this?
Why does tell Dante Dante you're a
And here's the truth.
Why is she engaging in this
dialogue, this Socratic dialogue?
What's the point of this?
Yes?
>> So, uh
I'm thinking that Dante hasn't fully
convinced himself that he is in heaven
yet, so his imagination is not
solidified there. So, if he un-convinces
himself that he's in heaven, then he
would just fall away and he would wake
up and he would be back on Earth. So,
Beatrice is trying to prevent that by
convincing him and by solidifying his
imagination in heaven.
>> Do you think this conversation actually
took place?
Okay, so what what's conversation
happening?
>> I think this is Dante Dante the poet
actually structuring it in such a way to
demonstrate the
and the difference between what what we
mentioned earlier, knowledge and
imagination.
>> Okay, actually yes.
>> Uh I think it's just for the reader to
so the reader can like reason it out
through like Dante Dante's experience in
heaven. So, like as a reader we
use logic
to understand Dante.
>> Okay, but I'm saying like why go through
this very long process? Why don't you
just tell us
what's going on?
Yes.
>> Well, I think it's just kind of the you
can call it a
emotional things or, you know, boy, they
don't just always think logically. They
sometimes think just
intuitively. That means we can call
original thinking. It's like uh Elon
Musk said original thinking is not the
the one but the zero. So,
>> Did Let me ask you this question. It's a
really weird question, okay? And we'll
end the first session with this
question.
Okay? The question is this.
Dante if wrote this in 1321,
did he could he possibly imagine that in
the year 2026
that we
would be in Beijing
on this day, it's a multicultural,
multilingual global
group and that we would be discussing
his Divine Comedy trying to figure out
his intention. Could he imagine this in
the year 1321?
What do you think?
It's pretty amazing, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Like like he wrote this
and it's only in the year 1321. He
didn't even know where China was.
That that never experienced the world.
Could he have imagined that in the year
2026 that we would be together
trying to
figure out
his intention. Could he have Could he
have imagined that?
Who says yes?
Someone say yes. Just for fun.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yes. I think it's a yes.
>> Why?
>> I think yes because just like
Shakespeare he said that uh maybe uh the
things that we can be forgotten but
words will be remembered forever. So,
every writer while their own uh work can
become masterpiece including thinking I
suppose. Yeah.
>> Uh yes.
>> I guess if what he writes is close to
the truth and close to what is true, it
will stand it stand the test of time,
right? And so it's still standing 3,000
50 years from now, 1,000 years from now,
2,000 years from now.
>> Yeah. Okay.
Good.
Right?
Um anyone else? Like like could he have
known that one day
we'd be reading this and discussing this
in Beijing
in 2026?
>> I don't know. Like maybe it has
Sorry. I don't know. Maybe when he was
on this journey he might have like
assumed that.
Like that's why he after 20 years he was
like very adamant that I would want to
be documenting this conversation and
leaving this work in something
vernacular so that more people could
like
>> Do you think actually
had this conversation happen? Do you
think any of this is actually true?
>> Uh yes, I suppose.
>> I think uh I think to analyze this you
need to strip the situation of its
trappings. So, you said we're here in
Beijing and we're here this group of
people specifically talking about it. Of
course, he could not have seen these
trappings. These are material trappings.
But
uh if we delve down into the architect
of what we're doing, which is discussing
his work, which is deriving knowledge,
deriving nourishment from it, then this
it architect is a constant across all
ages that he could absolutely have
foreseen that this was going to happen.
>> Okay. That's right. So, 500 years from
now, is it possible that another group
of people will be watching this video
and analyzing
what we're discussing? Is Is that
possible?
What would make it possible?
Why would they be doing this?
Well, they'll [clears throat] be reading
Dante.
They'll be reading Dante. I'm not sure
if they'll be watching the video.
They'll be reading Dante. But, how can
you be sure they'll be reading Dante?
Uh yeah yeah yes?
Yeah yeah go ahead.
>> Um well, maybe because
like Dante knew that Facebook would
change the course of history or we would
think in this room that they
>> He didn't even know that.
>> Well, not for sure, sir.
>> Oh, he actually did know that. He Yes,
he did.
Okay. He did know that when he wrote
this.
What happened to him after he finished
Divine Comedy? Do you guys know?
Died. He died. Right after he finished
Divine Comedy, he died.
>> Yeah yeah.
>> Oh.
>> Yeah.
He died.
>> Oh.
>> Yes?
>> Well, I think um these topics are
eternal and that's what make us human.
So, even after maybe 5,000 years or
somebody will still um learn from these
topics and try to um learn from people
that's um taught taught these topics
before.
>> Okay. Uh yes?
>> Yeah, I was going to
I was going to expand upon that um and
just say that people are going to
forever have curiosity and uh seek
questions about God and they will never
be answered until we die and die out.
>> Yeah, okay. So,
um I would just say that
if you just look into your heart,
you know what is eternal, what is true,
okay? And you know it that is eternally
and what is true, then you know that
this will both extend into the future
as well as extend back in the past,
okay? And it's something that you can't
actually It's hard to explain. It's
something that is just done through
faith and intuition, okay? All right.
So, we'll end the morning session on
this note and then we'll come back at
1:00.
All right?
Okay. All right. Thanks.
>> [applause]
>> Okay. Uh welcome back to the live
stream. Um so uh for those of you
watching online, please note that every
day we start class promptly at 10:00.
Then we'll break at 12:00 for lunch.
Uh and then we'll come back at 1:00. We
continue till 3:00, okay? So, the live
stream is from 10:00 a.m. until 3:00
p.m. But please note there's an hour
break in between. Um [clears throat]
just so that we can rest and get some
food to uh eat. Okay. So, um again, for
the first day we're establishing themes
and ideas that structure the Divine
Comedy. And then um after we do that,
then I'm I want to expand and give you
questions and exercises that help you
promote your intuition and your your
imagination. Because that's what's going
to allow you to fully understand the
Divine Comedy. Something that's really
important for you guys to keep in mind
is that right now uh I'm offering you my
interpretation, okay? Another caveat
that's very important is that we are
reading this in English. This is one of
dozens of translations. So, there's
going to be problems in interpretation
because we we because we don't speak
Italian. So, if you really want to
understand the Divine Comedy, if you
really want to experience starting for
yourself, you have to read aloud the
Divine Comedy in Italian as it was
designed, okay? And like it was it's a
And like the thing that
is
um the thing that I believe all the
Divine Comedy is that
it's an act of divine inspiration.
Meaning that Dante wrote this
um
by channeling God and the universe.
And only by reading aloud the Italian,
the Tuscan, can you experience this for
yourself, okay? Because when you do so,
you will be channeling Dante himself.
So, um
I hope that this class will only be the
beginning of a lifelong journey, okay? I
mean it'll be a lifelong journey into
truly experiencing
uh
Dante. Um another thing that I do in
this class, which may be a little bit
weird, is
I treat the Divine Comedy as perfection.
Meaning that every word, every idea
is perfect. And if we don't understand
it, it's because of the limitations of
our own intuition and imagination. Okay,
does that make sense? Okay, so if we're
being a bit confused, it's not his
fault, it's our fault.
Um and
uh I work under this assumption.
All right. Okay, so let's continue from
uh let's continue. Uh can you can you
read uh Carol? And thanks so much for
for reading, by the way.
>> Thank you.
Now, just as the sub matter of the snow
beneath the blows of the warm rays is
stripped of both its former color and
its cold,
so is your mind left bare of error.
I would offer now to you a new form,
light so living that it trembles in your
sight.
>> Okay, so the idea here is
if you truly want to understand
something, you need to engage in debate,
right?
Because this is the year 1321 and the
idea is just obey the Catholic Church,
just obey your priest and you'll
understand. And what finally is saying
no, you have to engage in open debate,
Socratic debate, if you truly want to
understand. So as a teacher,
you have to allow your students to make
errors, okay?
All right, keep on going.
>> Within the heaven of the godly peace
revolves a body in whose power lies the
being of all things that it enveloped.
>> Okay, all right. So this is really
interesting and I I want to
think about this.
So,
um
the metaphor that's being used is body,
all right?
The universe is a body,
okay? So, as an exercise,
I want to
think about what other metaphors we
could use to describe the universe,
right? The metaphor that's being used
here is body.
>> [snorts and clears throat]
>> But I want to explore other
possibilities.
What are some other possibilities
for how to describe the universe?
Anyone?
Yes?
>> A big ball.
>> A big ball. Okay, a big ball.
All right, that's interesting.
What else? Yes?
>> God.
>> God itself, okay, that's a possibility.
What else?
>> In Chinese mythology, they describe it
as a
turtle that's standing on top of an
elephant that's standing on top of
something else.
>> I don't know how I don't know how how to
describe that, okay?
Turtle
on top of elephant.
So, is it fair to say that there are
multiple dimensions
and they're all interlocking.
Okay, so maybe
uh interlocking dimensions. Okay.
This is new to me.
You guys are far more creative than I
am. Yes, what else?
>> Press on the mic.
>> Energy and vibration.
>> Okay, uh energy, sure. What else?
Yes?
>> Uh the soul.
>> Hm?
>> The soul.
>> Okay, the soul.
Okay, what else?
>> Uh
uh have have a cave.
>> A cave, okay, that's interesting. Okay.
Again, you guys are far more creative
than I am. I would not never come up
with these on my own. Anyone else?
Okay, how about garden?
Okay?
How about
a
factory?
>> Um there's a TV show that describes the
universe as a Jeremy Bearimy. So,
there's an I and then so like
the word Jeremy Bearimy because the word
Jer- Jeremy and
the J the J and the Y connect. So, the
idea is that the universe is a loop that
goes in a Jeremy Bearimy, but then
there's a I and if you accidentally end
up on that I, you're stuck forever.
>> This is way too complicated for for me.
Uh okay, all right. Okay, this is like
beyond my intention, okay? All right. My
The point I'm trying to make is that
depending on metaphor, you will perceive
the universe in a different way, okay?
So, if you just say the energy is the
universe is energy, it's basically
complete chaos, right?
Chaos and randomness.
Um to say the soul, it's like a fractal,
right?
Basically, your soul is
a universe
and then it mirrors the entire universe,
okay?
Uh, a cave is basically just a
simulation. Is that Is that fair to say?
A cave would be a simulation. It's not
real.
Okay.
Uh,
a
uh, God would be
um, the mind of God, okay? We're living
in a dream, basically.
Now, ball I I would not know how to
describe a ball, but a ball I think
would be What What would you say it's a
ball?
>> I should have clarified. I mean like a
crystal ball, like a little simulacrum,
and inside is everything, and you can
shake it up and it'll change a little.
>> So, so it's still a simulation?
>> No, no, not a sim- simulation. It's a
ball which contains everything, which is
more like a crucible, a reactor.
>> Yeah, I'm so confused.
>> A reactor.
>> Okay.
Um, okay.
So, a garden is something like God
um, as the gardener, right? Does that
make sense? We're all just a flower in
the garden. God's always taking care of
us, right? Nurturing us,
cultivating us. A factory is like a
machine
where there are certain laws to the
universe, and we're governed by these
laws, okay?
So, the ball The I think a body is
interesting because it is distinct from
all other of these metaphors.
Why would What What What What What does
a body signify?
All right, you have a body, you have a
brain, you have arms.
Why would that be a good metaphor for
the universe?
Uh, yes?
>> Uh, like it would mean that we are like
really part of the universe, and that we
can also reflect like upon ourself
compared to the universe, like what it
is.
>> Yes, thank you. Yes.
>> directly interact with it.
>> Uh just that the body is a metaphor for
the universe as in as a human the body
is all that there is.
Everything is contained within.
>> Okay, yes.
>> Um in a body there are organs and they
all have a purpose and they all work
together. So everything is connected. So
there's two things. One is everything is
connected. Two is everything has a role.
>> Good, yes.
>> A body can like receive ideas and then
enact them.
>> The brain, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So basically what and so what what's a
brain?
>> Ideas or the mind.
>> Okay. Anyone else? Yes. Maybe at the
back?
>> Um maybe the body of Christ or something
each has a role or like the head will be
leadership and then the other parts
hands or feet are like the actions.
>> Yes.
>> A body can die.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, a body can die. Yeah, okay.
Uh
yeah. All right. Yes?
>> Maybe the cells cuz body has cells,
right?
>> Yeah, many many more. So
interconnectedness. Yes, okay.
>> Stars is like cells.
>> [clears throat]
>> I guess it's interesting that if if
humans are the image of God and then
he's taking this metaphor as the
universe and he's creating a metaphor as
the image of of humans as well.
>> Right. Yes.
Right. So
the universe is a human as well. Yes.
Anyone else?
Okay. So some key ideas that we want to
remember um that we can construe from
body from the using body as a metaphor
for the universe is first of all
interconnectedness, right?
Everything is interconnected together.
Um
the role
meaning every part of the body is
important, right? If you lose a finger,
if you lose a cell, it's going to cause
problems for you. The last of is and
this is really important is that of
intentionality.
Intentionality.
A body cannot be random, right? Energy
can be random,
um but a body there has to be some
intentionality, a design to it.
The the body has a purpose. It has
direction. Right? It's not just random
chaos.
So, that's the idea
uh inherent in the body metaphor. Okay?
All right, let's continue.
>> The sphere that
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
The sphere that follows, where so much
is shown to varied essences bestow that
being to stars distinct and yet
contained in it.
The other spheres in ways diverse direct
the diverse powers they possess so that
these forces can bear fruit, attain
their aims.
So, these organs of the universe
proceed, as you now see, from stage to
stage, receiving from above and acting
downward.
>> Okay, so all these different spheres
that we see in the heavens, they're like
organs in a body, right? And what's
really important to understand is that
each organ has its own distinct role and
purpose.
If you lose an organ,
that's a problem, okay?
So, there's an intentionality
uh in each
sphere has a certain purpose, and it's
all to a design, okay? All right, keep
on going.
And and by the way, we'll be visiting
these spheres one by one, okay? Keep on
going.
>> Um so do So do these organs of the
universe proceed, as you now see, from
stage to stage, receiving from above and
acting downward. Now, do you attend
to how I pass by way of reason to the
truth you want that, then you may learn
how to cross the ford alone.
>> To cross the ford alone means to learn
so that you can be fully independent,
right? You are in this class in order to
be able to read the Divine Comedy by
yourself one day.
All right, keep on going.
>> The force and motion of the holy spheres
must be inspired by the blessed movers,
just as the smith imparts the hammers
art.
And so, from the deep mind that makes it
wheel, the sphere that many lights adorn
receives that stamp of which it then
becomes the seal.
>> So, God is the brain, and all the
spheres are different organs, okay? Keep
on going.
>> And as the soul within your dust is
shared by different organs, each most
suited to a different potency, so does
that mind unfold and multiply its bounty
through the varied heavens. Though that
intellect itself revolves upon a unity.
>> Okay.
>> With the dear body that it quickens, and
with which, as life in you, it too is
bound, each different powers forms a
different compound. Because of the glad
nature of its source, the power mingled
with the sphere shines forth as gladness
through the living pupil shine.
From this, and not from matter rare or
dense, derive the differences from light
to light. This is the forming principle,
producing, conforming with its worth,
the dark, the bright.
>> Okay, all right. So, do you guys
understand the point here?
I know that in school you study
evolution, you study physics, and you
believe that the universe is emergent,
meaning there are some basic principles,
and then from this will emerge other
things, okay? And what Dante is saying
is that's just a wrong way to understand
the universe. There is intentionality.
There is interconnectedness.
And the reason why the moon shines
differently
from other spheres
is that God manifests differently in
different places.
Okay? And it's all to a certain design
and intention.
And Peter says, "You must understand
this idea if we are to move on, okay?"
So, before we move on, are there any
questions?
Yes?
>> How could like like why why could our
understanding of the world as having
evolved from basic principles not
not coin
>> Is there any answer to this?
Does that anyone respond to this idea?
Why why is this in You're You're You're
asking like why is this in
contradiction, right?
Okay, well, I mean like there's a debate
between evolution and intelligent
design, right?
Where the people who believe in
evolution
said, "It is not because of God. It's
not because of intention. It's because
of survival of fittest. Because of
Darwinism, right?"
And so, what is the the the the the
question?
>> Can you try to hide the use the handheld
maybe?
You have to turn it on.
Yeah, so like why could not God not have
designed Darwinism? God designed
Darwinism and allowed Darwinism to take
its course because that's what God
wants.
>> Okay, so um this is a different
conception of God, okay?
So, there are you can say that God is an
architect who designed the rules of the
universe
and no longer cares.
Does that make sense?
Because he's already designed the game
and we just play the game and he doesn't
really care what happens.
What Dante is saying is like, "No,
God is still with us." And God
um shows his approval by shining his
light in us. Does that make sense?
All right.
Okay, do
do you do you understand this idea?
>> It's the difference between a game
developer and a game game master who
plays his own game.
>> Uh it's it's a it's a rough metaphor,
yes, but but yeah, the idea is that um
in evolution, what they're saying is
that
the universe is independent of God.
Does that make sense?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, God doesn't interfere in the
universe. What Beatrice is saying to
Dante is like, "No, God is always
present. We know because the spheres
shine differently."
Okay?
All right.
Any more questions before we move on?
It's really important you guys make sure
you understand. Otherwise, you'll
you'll get more and more confused as we
go along.
Yes?
>> Uh so you you you you you mean the God
is like uh you know, the sun or we are
just like a mirror, so the God is just
shine upon all all of us and we can
reflect the God back?
>> Right, so the metaphor that Beatrice
uses the body, right? So, God is the
brain.
Okay? So, we're always inter-
interfacing with with God.
All right?
Okay. All right, let's continue to canto
three, please.
>> That sun which first had warmed my
breast with love had now revealed to me
confuting, proving the gentle faith of
truth its loveliness.
And I
>> Sorry, what is the sun?
Apollo, but what else?
God, and what else?
>> Inspiration.
>> Okay, God
uh Apollo and what else?
Who's talking Who Who's he talking to?
>> Beatrice.
Right? So, how can we reconcile this?
This is a paradox.
Which Who Who's he talking to?
God or Apollo or Beatrice?
This is a paradox.
So, how can we reconcile this?
Yeah?
>> So, I'm going to borrow from William
I'm I'm going to borrow from William
Blake here. So, William Blake has his
gods and he also has the gods'
emanations. You can consider emanations
as representatives of the god. So,
Beatrice here is on behalf of Apollo and
on behalf of God in a more concrete form
in order to show Dante.
>> Exactly. Okay. Does that make sense to
you guys? Okay.
Ultimately, the secret is that God is
love, okay? And love can take different
manifestations. We can use different
ways to describe this love. It can
manifest itself as Apollo, it can
manifest itself as Beatrice, but it's
really the same force, okay?
All right. Okay, let's go back here and
go on.
>> And I, in order to declare myself
corrected and convinced, lifted my head
as high as my confessional required.
But a new vision showed itself to me.
The grip in which it held me was so fast
that I did not remember to confess.
Just as returning through transparent,
clean glass, or through waters calm and
crystalline, so shallow that they
scarcely can reflect
the mirrored image of our faces meets
our pupils with with no greater force
than that a pearl has when displayed on
a white forehead.
So faint the many faces I saw keen to
speak, thus my mistake was contrary to
that which led the man to love the
fountain.
As soon as I had noticed them, thinking
that what I saw were merely mirroring, I
turned around to see who they might be,
and I saw nothing.
And I let my sight turn back to meet the
light of my dear guide, who as she
smiled glowed in her holy eyes.
"There's no need to wonder if I smile,"
she said, "because your reason like a
child. Your steps do not yet rest upon
the truth.
Your mind misguides you into emptiness.
What you are seeing are true substances,
placed here because their vows were not
fulfilled.
>> Okay, so
Dante is um
in the spheres,
and he sees people, and he's completely
confused by this. Because why why is
this happening, right? Why is everyone
not with God? Why are people separated
from God, okay? And Beatrice is saying
um is trying to explain to him. Keep on
going.
>> "You're Okay, thus speak and listen.
Trust what they will say. The truthful
light in which they find their peace
will not allow their steps to turn
astray."
Then I turned to the shade that seemed
most anxious to speak, and I began as
would a man bewildered by desire to
intend.
"Oh spirit born to goodness, you who
feel beneath the rays of the eternal
life that sweetness which cannot be
known unless it is experienced. It would
be gracious of you to let me know your
name and fate.
At this, unhesitant, with smiling eyes,
our charity will never lock its gates
against just will. Our love is like the
love that would have all its court be
like itself.
Within the world I was a nun, a virgin,
and if your mind attends and recollects,
my greater beauty here will not conceal
me. And you will recognize me as
Piccarda, who placed here with the other
blessed ones, and blessed within the
slowest of the spheres. Our sentiments,
which only serve the flame that is the
pleasure of the Holy Ghost, delight in
their conforming to his order.
And we are
to be found within a sphere this slow
because we have neglected vows, so that
in some respect we were deficient.
>> Wait, so this is really interesting,
okay? So, there's a hierarchy to the
heavens, and at the very bottom are
those who are inconstant, meaning those
who have failed to fulfill their vows.
Okay?
So, keep on going.
>> And I to her,
"Within your wonderful semblance there's
something divine that glows,
transforming the appearance you once
showed.
Therefore, my recognizing you as low,
but what you now have told me is of
help. I can identify you much more
clearly."
>> Okay, so Piccarda is like someone that
Dante, the historical figure, knew in
real life, okay? So, throughout the
Divine Comedy, there are mythical
mythical figures, but there are also
people who were part of Dante's life.
Now, some background
background about Dante is that he was
essentially an aristocrat in Florence
who participated in uh politics. There
was a There was many struggles for power
in Florence.
And
>> [clears throat]
>> this was true for throughout Italy,
okay? And this power struggle is
something that we'll discuss as we as
move along, okay? But just remember
there's a power struggle for Piccarda
someone that Dante knew in real life.
You want to go ahead?
>> But tell me, though you're happy here,
do you desire a higher place in order to
see more and to be still more close to
him?
Together with her fellow shade, she
smiled at first, then she replied to me
with such gladness, like one who burns
with love's first flame.
Brother, the power of love appeases our
will so. We only long for what we have.
We do not thirst for greater
blessedness.
Should we desire a higher sphere than
ours, then our desires would be
discordant with the will of him who has
assigned us here.
But you'll see no such discord in these
spheres. To live in love is here
necessity, if you think on love's nature
carefully.
The essence of this blessed life
consists in keeping to the boundaries of
God's will, through which our wills
become one single will.
So that as we're arranged from step to
step throughout this kingdom, all this
kingdom wills that which will please the
king whose will is rule.
And in his will there is our peace.
That's the to which all beings move. The
beings he creates or nature makes, such
is his will.
>> Okay, so Dante asked her question. The
question is clearly there's this is
hierarchy in heaven and you are in the
outer sphere,
right? You're The core is God. So, do
you desire as a person to move closer to
God? Basically, graduate, right? To move
from the outer sphere to the inner
sphere.
What is her response?
>> No.
>> Why not?
>> She said we are content here.
>> Yeah, but why?
Yes?
>> Uh she is content because she has to be
absolutely obedient to God and God says
that you she has to be content here. So,
she has to be content. If she is not
content, then she will not even be
worthy of this first sphere.
>> Okay, yeah. Does that make sense, guys?
Okay, that's exactly what she says. But,
what's a paradox here?
What's a paradox here?
Yeah?
>> Her Her free will couldn't get her
higher.
>> Right, but she But she doesn't want to
go higher.
>> That's the thing though, right?
>> Yeah, so then God's God's making the
decision for her, though.
>> Right.
That's right, and she accepts that that
decision. But, that's a paradox. Why?
>> Uh it would place God as a judge and we
said that he wasn't
putting persons into places.
>> Right. No, I But, that's my
interpretation. I'm saying like like
within the structure, there's a paradox.
What's the paradox?
There's a logical contradiction here.
She says
God has willed me to be here and it is
my role, my duty to obey his will.
Therefore, I'm happy where I am.
But, what's the problem with this with
with this logic? Yes?
>> Um so,
I'm thinking, say this is the first
sphere and there's the second sphere and
eventually someone will have to advance
from the first sphere to the second
sphere, right? And the second sphere is
supposed to be better than the first
sphere, so you'll be happier in the
second sphere than you were in the first
sphere. However, according to this
logic, one can never advance, one can
never change because if you want to
advance to the second second sphere,
then you are not even worthy of the
first sphere. If you don't want to
advance to the second sphere and God
forced you to advance to the second
sphere anyways, then you will be less
happy in the second sphere than you were
in the first sphere, which is not
fitting with the second sphere.
>> Yeah, it makes absolutely no sense. Do
you do you understand the logic here,
right?
If if it if it was just a case where do
you just obey God's will and then
everyone's in heaven, there'd be no
hierarchy in heaven.
Why is there a hierarchy?
Does that make sense?
Okay? So, why is she stuck where she is?
Why is she in the lower sphere?
To me?
>> Cuz she's contented.
>> Yeah, cuz she's happy where she is.
Right? She wants to be there.
That's a problem.
Okay? All right.
All right, do you guys understand this?
All right. Okay, let's let's keep on
reading, Carol.
>> Then it was clear to me how every place
in heaven is in paradise. So, grace does
not rain equally from the high good.
But just as when our hunger has been
stated with one food one food, we still
long to taste the other. While thankful
for the first, we crave the latter.
So, was I in my words and in my gestures
asking to learn from her what was the
web of which her shuttle had not reached
the end.
A perfect life, she said, and her high
merit in heaven up above, a woman whose
rule governs those who in your world
would wear nun's dress and veil, so that
until their death, they wake and sleep
with that spouse who accepts all vows
that love conforms unto his pleasure.
Still young, I left the world to follow
her, and in her order's habit, I
enclosed myself and promised my life to
her rule.
Then men more used to malice than to
good took me violently from my sweet
cloister.
God knows what after that my life
became.
This other radiance that shows itself to
you at my right hand, a brightness
kindled by all the light that fills our
heaven, she has understood what I have
said. She was a sister, and from her
head, too, by force, the shadow of the
sacred veil was taken.
But though she had been turned back to
the world against her will, against all
honest practice, the veil upon her heart
was never loosed. This is the splendor
of the great Costanza, who from the
Swabians second gust engendered the one
who was their first, their third, and
final power.
>> let me explain what's going on, okay? So
Dante is asking her, "Um, why are you
here?"
And she says,
"Well, what happened was that, um, my
brother is this very powerful duke,
and I fell in love with God, and I
wanted to serve God, so I followed,
um, a woman into the nunnery, okay? I
became a nun, right? I made my vows to
God. My brother, the duke, needed me as
a pawn for his
power politics, right? He wanted to
marry me off to to someone else to form
an alliance. So, he sent his soldiers
to force me
back to him and then he married me off.
But, even though I was married, even
though I gave children, I never
abandoned my love for God. In my heart,
I maintained
loyalty to God. So, even though my body
uh no longer was chaste, my heart was
chaste.
Okay? And it's not just me, but my
friend here
same situation where she was also a nun,
and she was also stolen to be married
off by her brother, okay?
And
so, it seems as though they've done
nothing wrong. Yet, at the same time,
they are in the lowest sphere, okay?
Which basically tells us God doesn't
really approve of their actions.
This is a paradox, right? They did
nothing right. They did nothing wrong.
They were forced to get married.
What did they do wrong?
>> They didn't
>> Nothing, right?
>> They didn't like have ambition. They
didn't try to exercise their free will.
>> Wait, wait, wait. How could they
exercise their free free will?
>> By refusing.
>> Yeah, but there are soldiers with swords
dragging her
away. What could she have done?
>> She could have tried to escape
or killed herself.
>> Okay, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Yeah?
>> Uh she she couldn't she couldn't offer
herself because uh in Catholicism that's
a that's a sin.
>> Exactly. Thank you. Yes. Yes. Okay. This
is a really important constraint, okay?
So, in the Catholic religion at this
time, the worst sin in the world is
suicide. You understand? If you kill
someone, that's not as bad as if you
kill yourself. So, suicide is the worst
sin.
Okay?
And why they made this a sin is it was
very common for women who are who are
raped to kill themselves. Why?
Yeah, but but why kill yourself?
>> No [clears throat] one wants to marry
them.
>> Right. But but they were Christians. You
understand? They were Christians. So,
they thought, "If I kill myself, I can
just be going with Jesus."
>> Oh, right.
>> And that's why the church has to say,
"No, you can't kill yourself anymore."
Okay? In fact, Augustine wrote an entire
essay on this saying like, "The worst
sin is suicide. Much more much worse
than rape because look, at the end of
the day, they're just raping your body.
They can't touch your soul, right? What
matters is your soul. Your body doesn't
matter.
Your body belongs to this earth, which
is nothing, but your soul belongs to
God, which is everything, okay? So,
don't worry if you get raped. Don't
worry if you get married. It doesn't
matter. What matters is your faith.
And what
So, why is she in the lowest sphere?
She did everything right. What's what's
wrong with this?
Yeah?
>> Uh then maybe God think that uh the body
or the soul is just what I give to you,
but if you just deny it, it means that
you deny me. So, maybe you need to be
tortured.
>> Okay.
Let's let's let's elaborate on on your
idea here.
Okay?
>> I think
>> You can't kill yourself, right? So, what
do you do?
>> [clears throat]
>> So, you you should run away.
>> But they'll just catch you.
Right?
>> Cuz that's
>> So, you fight back
like a Disney princess. Like you fight
back.
>> You fight back?
>> Yes.
>> Yes? [clears throat]
>> Well, actually I was going to say that
what about if she used the free will and
she does fight back and dies honorably
and then it's not really suicide.
>> It's still suicide.
>> But is Dante saying that in this case
suicide is okay? Like is he going
against
>> Sure. Dante would never say suicide is
okay.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Well, what what what what again
like like what's going on here?
>> Is he Is he trying to
kind of
criticize the
the the Christian churches?
>> No. Okay. No, he did he Yeah?
>> [clears throat]
>> Could it be bringing
randomness and luck into this at all?
The she she had a bad luck.
>> Does Does Does Dante believe in in
randomness and luck?
Okay. Yes.
>> So,
uh
this lowest fear is for people who have
broken their promises. When you enter a
nunnery, you make a vow to be chaste, to
be a virgin forever. And no matter how
you did it, no matter who forced you to
do this, you still broke that promise in
the eyes of God. And so God will assign
you where you need to go.
>> I I understand this, but this morning we
just said that God was all forgiving,
all loving, and not judgmental. This is
clearly judgmental. Clearly she did
nothing wrong. Why is she here?
>> [clears throat]
>> What's going on here, guys?
Yeah?
>> And forgive herself, so she confined
herself to that sphere.
>> Yeah. Well, that that is true. She she
she did say that, "I belong here and I'm
happy here."
Right? But But the question is like how
did she end up here? That's the
question, right?
What did she do wrong? She clearly did
something wrong. What was it?
Okay.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, I'm going to write down a phrase,
okay? And you guys have all heard this
phrase before, but you tell me what it
means.
Where
there
is a will
>> There is a way.
>> [clears throat]
>> There is a way. What does it mean?
>> Like how Rapunzel was stuck in the
tower, she escaped. So, if she had a
will if she if she had a will to escape,
she could have escaped. And even if she
died, she would have been she would have
died honorably in trying to exercise her
free will.
>> Okay, anyone else?
I I don't understand how this works.
Where there is a will, there is a way.
What does this mean? Okay, yeah, you
really want to escape and you escape,
but but how does that work?
Yeah?
>> Well, you like manifest a way or like
you imagine a way in your mind out of it
and then some in some way the universe
will give you a way to get there.
>> Exactly, okay. Could you Could you
repeat that? This is exactly This is
exactly it, okay?
Okay, make sure everyone understands
this idea. Say Say it again.
>> Well, the if you like can imagine
the world that you want, then
you the the universe will be able to
showcase a way for you and then you will
be able to walk it.
>> Does that make sense to you guys? Okay,
let me let me explain the process. First
of all is the will. You really really
want it. Okay? When that happens is you
don't know how an idea
will come into your mind. You will
imagine a way.
And then what happens is that this
manifestation, this imagination,
the universe will respond and shape
reality in a way that allows you to
manifest
your will. Does that make sense, guys?
Okay? So, the problem
is that she did not want it enough.
Do you understand?
It is not she vocal will, it's just she
was not faithful enough.
If you really want to escape, then an
idea would have come to your mind to
show you the way.
And then you just go do it and the
universe bends reality in a way that
allows you to escape.
Okay? But the key is the will.
Right?
And what he's saying is like you can
have anything you anything you want, the
universe will grant it to you. The
question is do you really really want it
or not? And clearly she did not.
And how do we know
she does not she didn't want it?
>> She's here.
>> She
Oh yeah, sure she's she's here, but what
else?
>> It happened to her anyways.
She
>> No, but what's the problem right now?
She doesn't want want to go anywhere
else, do you understand?
That's the problem.
>> Oh.
>> It's not that she's here, it's like she
doesn't want to go beyond this point.
She's like, "I'm perfectly happy here,
man. I went to heaven, I'm awesome, you
know? Like I went to Yale, I'm the worst
student at Yale, but I'm happy being the
worst student at Yale."
Like that's like literally what she's
saying.
Okay?
Right?
All right.
Any more questions?
This This is This is a really important
idea if you if you want to understand
Dante, okay?
You are always in communication with the
universe.
Right? It's only a question of like how
focused, how intentional,
how much will do you have in achieving
what you want?
All right? So, if you don't get Yeah?
>> I I just want to add that like um
that's what like free will is about.
Like free will is not just being able to
do what you what you want, but like
being able to will what you want.
>> Exactly.
>> It's all It's more about the will than
like the the action.
>> Yeah, that's exactly correct. Yes. Yes?
>> Is that like Nietzsche's will to power
idea, or is it different?
>> Okay, let's just say for whatever reason
you want to become
king, right?
And what's the question?
>> Is then is this idea about will kind of
the same as Nietzsche's idea about will
to power? Like
>> Yes. Yes, it's very similar. Yes.
>> Is it It It reminds me of a concept we
learned in psychology where it's called
self-efficacy as brought up by Bandura.
The idea is that um
like
the number one reason why you're able to
accomplish something is you believing in
yourself that you can accomplish that
thing.
>> Exactly. Right. It It It It's It's the
word we we It's It's like we The popular
phrase is manifestation. You understand?
You manifest it. Okay, meaning you
imagine it, but you you're able to
imagine it cuz you will it into being,
right? Which Which is Nietzsche's point,
okay? And I mean, like it's really
important to understand
that
um what they're all saying is that
there's really no good and evil in the
universe. There's just will, okay? And
so, it's entirely your choice how to
live it. And And I know this sounds a
bit weird, but um we'll try to unpack it
as we go along, okay? This This idea
here, okay? Uh you also had had a had a
comment or a question?
>> Yeah, I just wanted to clarify. Does she
like not want to escape by the north or
does she not want to send to the next
sphere by the north?
>> Okay, all right. So so so so let's go
deeper into this. Okay, you're Bakr.
Okay, you're in a convent. You're happy
in the convent.
Soldiers come to you. Okay, let let's
try to imagine
her state of mind. What what is she
thinking?
What what are some emotions going
through her mind? What what is she
thinking right now? She's in a convent.
There's like an army like on on the
convent demanding that she go with them.
Right? And they're they're like mean.
They have like swords. They
They're really mean people. And like
quite honestly, they could come and kill
everyone in the convent, right? What is
she thinking right now?
What what is her thought process?
>> Feel like she's um really in despair
because obviously as like one woman she
um cannot face off this group of people.
>> Fear and despair, right?
>> Yeah, and then maybe like she will pray
to God because like hopefully God will
save her, but maybe it wasn't like
strong enough.
>> And and and what will God Yeah Yeah,
sorry. What will What will God say to
this? You're You're You're afraid.
You're in despair. You pray to God.
Please save me. Please save me. Please
save me.
So what's wrong with that?
Yeah?
>> Well, um I just wanted to say that God
just needs your trust. So if you trust
God and you love God enough then you
wouldn't fear death and you wouldn't be
afraid of the soldiers.
>> Yeah, that's the problem. The fear is a
problem.
You understand?
The fact that you fear means you don't
really truly believe in God. It truly It
doesn't It tells uh God you don't really
really want to be saved. Okay? It's that
fear.
You understand?
Okay?
So that's why she's stuck where she is
because she's afraid. It's not like
she's happy, but she's afraid of the
unknown.
She's afraid of that leap of faith that
you have to put into God.
That's her limitation.
Yeah?
>> Can I ask a follow-up question? So, is
it still possible for her to change in
heaven? Like maybe develop like a will
to advance or
>> Of course it is. What's the problem?
>> Oh, so um at first I thought like what
she did as a human like defined like
where she will go in like heaven and
>> Uh no, it doesn't.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Yeah. But but what's the problem with
her?
>> Um like she doesn't want to advance.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? Okay?
And and why And why Why doesn't she want
to?
>> Um
>> What's the reason why she doesn't want
to change?
>> like content or like
>> No, it's not because she's content. It's
because
But why doesn't she have a will?
She's afraid. Do you understand? It's
the fear. Do you understand?
>> Oh, okay. Okay.
>> Right? It's a fear.
>> So, it's her that she's she's scared
that like she cannot advance or
>> Yeah, she's afraid of disappointment.
She's afraid of failure.
>> Oh, okay. Okay.
>> Right? So, she's stuck saying, "Okay,
well, God just wants me here.
>> So, I'm just going to stay here."
>> Yeah. It's a It's a pretext. It's a
rationale.
>> So, it's like comforting yourself when
you got like a bad grade or something.
Right?
>> It's Yeah, it's a very human reaction.
We do this all the time, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> We We say we're happy, you know, being
the worst student at Yale.
But
you're not. Okay?
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. Yeah, I get it. Thank you.
>> All right. Any more questions or
comments?
Yeah?
>> Oh, yeah. So, I just want to know the
difference between the worship and the
believe. For example, I believe in God,
but it doesn't mean that I worship God
because as a worship is a higher much
higher believed than
>> Does God care if you worship him or not?
Does God care if you worship him or not?
Does God care if you're Christian or
not?
Yeah, it's also like it doesn't matter,
do you understand?
What matters are your actions, right?
What matters if it is your actions that
define who you are.
Right? If you are
Piccarda and you're like if you
like okay, let let's let's use your
imagination.
There's a
army
outside the convent, okay?
The army says, you come out now or come
in and we'll kill everyone in the
convent, okay?
And Piccarda is fearless.
And she has total faith in God. What
could she have done to get herself out
of the situation?
Guys, use your use your imagination.
What could she have done? Imagine
yourself as Piccarda.
You're in the convent, yeah?
>> Maybe like I won't actually do it, but I
will probably pretend to suicide or
whatever. Like if you guys dare to come
in now, I'll just kill myself.
>> Yeah, do you understand this? You just
stand on top of the roof and say, "Okay
guys, you come in the door, I'll jump
jump down."
Right?
If you're the army, what's your job
again?
What's your job as the army?
>> To get her safely to the convent.
>> Exactly, right?
And so, what would the army do?
>> Try to go up to the castle and like
bring her down.
>> No, they won't.
They'd be afraid,
right? Cuz where are they now?
No, no, no, I'm saying where are they?
What what what building or or or is in
front of them?
>> God.
>> God is in front of them, you understand?
Who do you think has taken possession of
Piccarda right now?
If you see a woman, okay, who's like a
princess, and she's standing on top of a
roof and says, "Hey guys, you come in,
I'll jump I'll jump down."
Who do you think you're fighting now?
God. You're fighting You're fighting God
now. Okay? And so, they're going to run
away.
Right? They go back
to the duke and says, "Hey man,
uh your sister's crazy."
What's the duke going to do?
Marry another woman. Well, he'll
probably calm himself, okay?
And now, he's outside the nunnery,
and she's doing the same thing again,
right? You come in, and I'll jump down
the the roof. What's he What's he going
to do?
>> Try to persuade her, but fail.
Maybe.
>> And then, what's he What's What's he
going to do?
>> Then go away.
>> He's He has to go home now.
You understand?
He's like, you can't deal with this
crap.
Right?
But But you see what's happened. Just
the will. Like, yeah?
>> Like, uh
this This is actually a question
directed at something you said earlier.
So, you said earlier that your actions
define where where where you are on this
celestial ladder. However, uh
spoilers, but but like, in Purgatory,
are the good pagans. So, the good pagans
who did not believe in God, but did good
deeds. So, if your deeds define who you
who you are, then why are the good
pagans stuck there?
>> Um okay, we have not read complete The
Divine Comedy.
What you find is that, even though the
Catholic Church says that
your Christianity determines if you go
to heaven or hell, Dante doesn't believe
this.
Okay?
Right? Doesn't make sense. As you keep
on reading, you'll find that there are
pagans who are in heaven.
Okay? [laughter]
>> So, there is no good then.
>> Yeah. All right. Yeah.
>> Um about the like the imaginative
situation that um when she that she says
that she's going to like fall off the
the castle, what if the soldiers just
think that she's lying and then like and
or or she says that but she doesn't
really believe it.
Would they still like come and get her
or would they be convinced by her?
>> Well, imagine if you were a soldier,
what would what you be thinking?
You mean?
>> She's bluffing.
>> Yeah. She could be bluffing.
And and and are you going to take the
chance?
>> No.
>> Probably.
>> You're not going to take a chance, do
you understand?
Okay, because
I I mean like okay.
I mean, you have to like imagine
yourself in that situation, okay? You're
the soldier. Ricardis is doing this crap
on you. Right?
You have to think God has taken
possession of her.
And and they are in a nunnery, do you
understand?
Okay, so the human reaction would be
like
I need to get out of here, man.
This is not a good situation situation
for me.
Right? Because if I go back and I tell
the Duke
uh your sister's crazy
and she won't come home, what what what
will the Duke do?
>> Off with your head.
>> Um
Well,
>> I think it's the problem with the
livelihoods because maybe they're paid
by the Duke and then like if they aren't
paid that they wouldn't be able to feed
like their families back home, I think.
>> Okay, well, imagine two situations. The
first situation is
you go back to the Duke and says, "Your
sister's crazy and
uh we have to like come back."
Second situation is like
"We thought your sister was bluffing, so
we stormed the nunnery and she jumped
off the roof and now she's dead.
>> Yeah, the first one's better.
>> The first one is probably better for
you, okay?
It's a lot better for you.
Right?
Okay? So, again, I'm not saying
uh this is what's going to happen. I'm
I'm saying like if you have the will,
there's always going to be a way.
And that's something that Dante is
trying to portray here, okay?
All right?
Okay. Uh let's keep on reading.
>> This said, she then began to sing Ave
Maria and while singing vanished as a
weighty thing will vanish in deep water.
My sight, which followed her as long as
it was able to, once she was out of
view, returned to where it greater
longing lay.
And it was wholly bent on Beatrice.
But she then struck my eyes with so much
brightness that I, at first, could not
withstand her force.
And that made me delay my question.
>> So, um Dante has met Piccarda and now he
wants to ask Beatrice a question. What
is his question?
We just spent the last hour talking
about it.
What question does Dante really, really
want to ask Beatrice now?
What did she do wrong, right?
Like I don't understand this at all. She
did nothing wrong.
Okay. All right. Uh let's continue to to
canto four.
>> [clears throat]
>> Before a man bit into one of two foods
equally removed and tempting, he would
die of hunger if his choice were free.
So would a lamb stand motionless between
the craving of two savage wolves. In
fear of both, so would a dog between two
deer.
Thus, I need neither blame nor praise
myself when both my doubts compelled me
equally. What kept me silent was
necessity.
>> So, Donny is very confused. So confused
that he's in fear. Okay? He has anxiety
over this. Again, the question is
what did Piccarda do wrong here?
He's really confused by this. Keep on
going.
>> [clears throat]
>> I did not speak. But in my face were
seen longing and questioning, more
ardent than if spoken words had made me
made them evident.
Then Beatrice did just as Daniel did
when he appeased Nebuchadnezzar's
Nebuchadnezzar's anger, the rage that
made the king unjustly fierce.
She said, "I see how both desires draw
you, so that your anxiousness to know is
self-tangled and cannot express itself.
Your reason, if my will to good
persists, why should the violence of
others cause the measure of my merit to
be less?"
>> Okay, so do you understand this, okay?
Piccarda, what did she do wrong? She was
forced
to leave the convent. She had no choice
in the matter. So, why is she stuck in
the lowest sphere? Okay? Keep on going.
>> And you're also led to doubt because the
doctrine Plato taught with fine support
by souls appearing to return to the
stars.
These are the questions that within your
will press equally for answers.
Therefore, I shall treat the most
insidious question first.
Neither the seraph closest unto God, nor
Moses, Samuel, nor either John,
whichever one you will, nor Mary, have,
I say, their place in any other heaven
than that which houses those souls you
just saw, nor will their blessedness
last any longer.
But all those souls grace the Empyrean,
and in each of them has gentle life,
though some sense the eternal spirit
more, some less.
They show themselves to you here not
because this is their sphere, but as a
sign for you that in the Empyrean their
place is lower.
>> Okay, okay, so this is a really
important idea to keep in mind, okay?
This is a metaphorical representation of
the heavens.
In the actual heavens, there is no time
and space, so there is no hierarchy.
Okay?
But there are certain souls
that
um are not as worthy as other souls, and
so they are now visually depicted in the
low in the lower spheres, okay? So this
is just an optical illusion
in order to for us to better understand
what's going on. Am I going?
>> Such signs are suited to your mind,
since from the senses only can it
apprehend what then becomes fit for the
intellect.
>> again, there's no time and space here.
Right? So only by
adding in time and space can we truly
understand what's going on.
Am I going?
>> And this is why the Bible condescends to
human powers, assigning feet and hands
to God, but meaning something else
instead.
And Gabriel and Michael, and the angel
who healed the eyes of Tobit, are
portrayed by holy church with human
visages.
That which Timaeus said in reasoning of
souls does not describe what you have
seen, since it would seem that as he
speaks he thinks.
He says the soul returns to that same
star from which, so he believes, it had
been taken when nature sent that soul as
formed to body.
>> Okay, all right. So, um
so the idea here is that we all come
from the soul world, okay? And in the
soul world uh we come with a purpose and
after we die we go back to the same
place that we come from.
But then this raises the question then
is what is the point of life then?
Right? If you're just going to end up in
the same place you started out with, who
cares what you do here?
All right? Uh yes,
do you have a comment or question?
>> Yeah, well, through like life on love on
Earth you can learn and have experiences
and then they can shape you and maybe
like make you more enlightened and um
help
>> Yeah, but you still end up end up in the
same place.
>> But that well
well, you could change, right? Like you
can change your your opinion by
yourself.
You will basically.
>> On this on this world but back in the
old world, the real world, the world of
heavens, you're still stuck where you
are.
But this is what Tim is saying, okay?
Not not what Donny is saying. Donny
Donny would obviously say that no, you
can actually ascend.
Yeah?
>> Uh so, I would say that's a very
materialist view of life. So, we're
going to die anyways, so why not have
fun? Like if you're stuck
if you're stuck there then all you have
is every day you can sing, I guess. But
here you can drink, you can drink beer,
you can have a wife, you could you could
do a lot of things and that's the fun of
the matters.
>> Why not? You know?
Like cuz you can't as you say you can't
get drunk and throw up up there, so do
it here, man.
Right? What what and like, you know,
have lots and lots of sex, man, and go
kill someone just for fun.
Right? What's stopping you?
Okay?
All right. I'm I'm saying go do these
things. I'm just saying like
you know, but anyway, you can keep on
going.
>> But his opinion is perhaps to be taken
in other guise than his words speak,
intending something not to be derided.
If to these fears he wanted to attribute
honor and blame for what they influence,
perhaps his arrow reaches something
true.
This principle, ill-understood, misled
almost all of the world one,
so that hope and Mercury and Mars gave
names to stars.
The other doubt that agitates you is
less poisonous,
for its insidiousness is not such as to
lead you far from me.
To mortal eyes our injustice seems
unjust, that this is so should serve as
evidence for faith, not heresy's
depravity.
But that your intellect may penetrate
more carefully into your other query, I
shall, as you desire, explain it
clearly.
If violence means that the one who
suffers has not abetted forces in any
way, then there's no excuse these souls
can claim.
For will, if it resists, is never spent,
but acts as nature acts when fire
ascends, though force a thousand times
tries to compel.
>> Okay, so here it she's explaining
exactly what we discussed, okay?
As long as you have the will, it becomes
like a fire ascending, and there's no
force in on our planet that can stop our
will.
You understand?
Same idea here, where if you really want
it, you're going to imagine
uh a solution that's a fire ascending,
and then the universe will will bend
itself to accommodate you.
Okay?
You can go on going.
>> So that when will has yielded much or
little, it has abetted force, as these
souls did. They could have fled back to
their holy shelter.
>> Okay, so yeah, that's it, okay? The
reason why
these soldiers were able to arrest you
and take you back is you let them do it.
You agreed to it. Don't say you were
forced to do it.
Okay? You could have run away. You could
You could have done a lot of things,
okay? Keep on going.
>> Had their will been as whole as that
which held Lawrence fast to the great
and that which made of Mucius, one who
judged his own hand, then once freed,
they would have willed to find the faith
from which they had been dried. But it
is all too seldom that a will is so
intact.
>> Okay, all right. So, Mucius is a great
story. Have you guys ever heard the
story of Mucius?
All right. So, what happened was
um
that
the Romans were a small republic and
they're surrounded by this huge empire.
They were under siege.
And they were starving.
So, one young nobleman, Mucius, and he's
like 20 years old, he he suggests that
he goes and assassinate the king.
Okay? So, he gets permission from the
father from the
uh Roman elders, the senators. He swims
across the Tiber, sneaks into the enemy
camp. And he's trying to assassinate the
king. The problem is that it's payday.
And so, there are two people on stage,
the king and the secretary. They both
look alike, they dress alike. Okay?
And so, Mucius is like, "Hmm.
I don't know who's the king. Right? I
have one dagger. I'm going to leave and
I'm going to kill someone,
but
I might miss. And
you know, it's 50/50, okay?
What would you do in that in in that
situation?
What would you do?
Hmm?
Well, you can't, right? You you
understand? If you kill one, the
soldiers have to come and arrest you.
Right? So, what do you do?
What would you do, seriously?
>> Uh maybe I would have to kill one of
them. I don't care who is real. I just
kill because I kill any man, it means my
will is there, so
>> Yeah, okay. So, most people just go home
or or like this way, okay? But Mucius is
like, "Screw this. I'm going to take a
chance, okay?" So, he kills one and it's
of course it's the secretary.
So, now he's arrested and the king says
to him, "You see that fire over there?
This fire is burning, okay? It's a
bonfire. And if you don't tell me
exactly who you work for
and how many
compatriots you have
and what your plan is, I'm going to burn
you in a bonfire."
Okay? You either confess and tell me
everything, I'm going to burn you alive.
So, what does Mucius do?
Yeah?
>> I think he like stuck his hand in the
fire and said that he's not afraid.
>> Yeah, that's what he does, okay? He just
put his hand
in
the fire and it's burning, okay? And
while this happening, he's laughing. And
the king is like,
"You Romans are such crazy bastards that
I'm going to go run away now."
>> [laughter]
>> Okay?
And so, this part is not a true story,
um but it shows the power of the will.
Whereas, as long as you believe, as long
as you are willing to act, the universe
will bend itself to
um your will.
Okay? And this is very different from
the idea of strategy, right? Or you
know, let's be really, really clever.
Okay?
This is something very different. This
is really power.
All right. Okay. Keep I keep
[clears throat] going?
>> And through these words, if you have
grasped their bent, you can eliminate
the argument that would have troubled
you again and often.
But now another obstacle obstructs your
ascent. You cannot overcome it by
yourself. It is too wearying to try.
I've set it in your mind as something
certain that souls in blessedness can
never lie, since they're always nearer
the primal truth. But from Piccarda, you
were also able to hear how Constance
kept her love of the veil. And here
Piccarda seems to contradict me.
Before this, brother, it has often
happened that to flee to flee menace,
men unwillingly did what should not be
done.
So did Alcmaeon.
To meet the wishes of his father, killed
his mother. Not to fail in filial piety,
he acted ruthlessly.
>> Okay, all right. So, often in life when
we make decisions,
we often contradict principles, okay?
So, for example, this man, uh Alcmaeon,
um his father ordered him to kill his
mother. Obviously, murder is wrong, but
you also have to respect your father,
right? Disobeying your father is wrong,
murdering your your mother is wrong.
What do you do?
Okay? Often in life we have these moral
dilemmas. And keep on going.
>> At that point, I would have you see the
forces to which one yielded mingles with
one's will. And no excuse can pardon
their joint act. Absolute will does not
concur in wrong, but the contingent
will, through fear that its resistance
might bring greater harm, consent.
Therefore, Piccarda means the absolute
will will when he she speaks, and I the
relative. So that the two of us have
spoken truth.
>> Okay, all right.
So, this is a really important idea we
need to unpack, okay? There's a
difference between absolute will
and relative will, contingent will.
What's the difference?
Yes?
>> So, absolute will is I will love God no
matter what and contingent will is I
will love God and then someone tells
you, "If you love God, I'll kill you."
And so you say, "Okay, okay, I don't I
don't."
>> Um okay, any other theories?
>> Let's say they come from different
places. Absolute will comes from
imagination, it comes from your own
story, but as relative will comes from
reasoning reasoning logic,
you know, comparing outcomes.
>> Okay, any other explanations?
Absolute will, contingent will. What's
the difference?
>> The same as absolute morality and
relative morality?
>> What's the difference between between
these two things?
>> So, I don't know, like absolute is that
no matter what it's going to happen, but
contingent it's kind of like
because I don't want more harm to be
done, kind of like what the book Silence
is about where the priest, the Catholic
priest, in order to protect the Japanese
believers said that they are going to
not be priests and take wives.
>> Okay.
Um
We're going to get to you then to you,
okay? Yeah.
>> Um I would say
contingent will is um constrained by
reality
and absolute will is like
it's always there,
like absolute will is God, basically.
Like the will of God.
>> And so, how can we describe these things
more simplistically? Absolute will is
what? Contingent will is what?
>> Can I answer? Yeah.
>> Hm?
>> Can I answer?
>> Yeah.
>> Um so, contingent will will it would be
the individual human and the absolute
will would be
by God's display on us.
>> And what is your connection to the God?
How How do you connect it to God?
>> Through
through love.
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah?
>> Um, so like I would say that absolute
will is active. It is the will that
finds the way. It creates its own
condition for it is unstoppable.
Contingent will operates within the
confines of the material. It reacts to
what is put before it in order to follow
itself. But
>> Right, right, right. So both both both
you and you are right, okay. But I'm
saying add it together, what do you get?
Like Like Like very very simplistically,
what is the difference? Yeah Yeah? Did
Did you have a comment or question?
>> Um, yeah, this is it's all not not
related. I think um, absolute will
would be faith and then um, contingent
will would be belief and one needs
justification, the other doesn't.
>> Okay, yeah.
>> Uh, absolute will is when you're aligned
with God and contingent is when you're
not.
>> Okay, but but but how can we say this
very simplistically?
>> Um, I'm going to give it a go try. So
maybe absolute will is like perfect and
then like um, contingent will is
imperfect so it will if you don't like
exercise it well, it will be like faulty
and lead to like bad things.
>> Okay.
All right. So like like let's put this
very simple, okay? Absolute will is the
soul, right? The soul is always in
connection with the God.
Contingent will is the body. The The
body needs respond to the material
universe, the material world. So the
contingent will can be afraid. So what
Beatrice is saying is that when
Pocahontas acting,
her absolute will was still true to God,
but her contingent will
um
defied God, okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay, but
but why would this be a problem?
Yeah?
>> I have a question. Do these two will,
can they coexist at the same time?
Absolute will and contingent
[clears throat] will.
>> Okay. So, um
Dante is putting this very
simplistically, okay? What he's saying
is that there are two wills, the
absolute will, your soul, the contingent
will, your body responds to
uh worldly problems.
But, um you can think of the will
existing in infinite dimensions.
Does that make sense? Infinite
dimensions.
So, there's infinite wills.
And
um
yeah.
And what what are you trying to do
as a person? You're trying to create
harmony across these infinite dimensions
of wills, okay? You're trying to align
the absolute will with a contingent
will.
And why would you want to do that?
Yeah?
>> Oh, yeah, maybe it's just like
I remember Bruce Lee once said that try
to be combined to harmony. So, maybe
in China maybe most people they just
like to keep balance. They don't like to
choose the two extreme, whether you're a
spiritual thing or whether a material
thing. They just
>> Yeah. Yeah, I understand that. Yes, keep
on going. Uh yes?
>> Well, if you align all contingent wills
and create absolute will, you create
godhoods or you become gods, right?
>> No, no, no, you're not trying to become
God. You're trying to be you're trying
to be close to God, you understand?
There's a difference.
>> But but like if you can't like
all the wills of the people, if you can
like
make them objective, then that would be
being like God.
So through doing that through power
like
>> No, that's not what Dante would say.
Some other people would say that but not
but not Dante, okay?
All right? So the idea here is
there are different
expressions, manifestations of your
will, okay? There's the absolute will
which is always in connection with God.
And then there's a contingent will which
is
your choices
on this world. And what we're trying to
do is we're trying to harmonize these
two
wills in order to become closer to God
in order to make the right decisions.
Okay? So for Karna in her instance, her
absolute will was loyal to God
but her contingent will
uh surrendered to fear.
Okay?
And that's what her problem was.
Does that make sense, guys?
Any questions? Before we move on, yeah?
>> Um so how can we combine these two wills
together?
Like better.
>> Uh any response to this?
How do you combine these two together?
>> Well, maybe because why people just feel
just scared about death because they
don't know where they're going to go,
right? But if we know where we're going
to go, there must be some kind of
universe in that place. Maybe they don't
need to scare about it. The fear is just
come from unknown. But if we know
something then we don't think the fear
>> Yeah, that's right. So historically
there've been two solutions, okay? The
first solution is knowledge.
Gnosis. So like just continue to read
Dante, explore, and just discover the
secrets of the universe. And once you
have the knowledge, you lose fear.
Right? Because why do you of are you
afraid of death? Because you're afraid
Because you're afraid that if you die,
you'll just be nothing. But if you
actually know the secrets of the
universe, you recognize that death is
just
a release, or it's just a beginning of
something else. So, you lose that fear,
okay? So, knowledge is one possibility,
but another possibility is the idea of
love.
Okay? To just love someone so intensely
that you give yourself to that person,
and you lose your fear. And when you
love someone unconditionally, what
happens is the absolute will and the and
the contingent will combine together.
Because all your actions are dictated by
your
uh love for that person. This is what
Dante will will tell us later on.
Okay, does that make sense? Knowledge or
love.
Okay.
All right. I Can you continue reading,
please?
>> Such was the rippling of the holy stream
issuing from the fountain from which
springs all truth. It set to rest both
of my longing.
Then I said, "Oh, beloved of the first
lover, oh you divine whose speech so
floods and warms me that I feel more and
more life.
However deep my gratefulness, it cannot
match your grace with grace enough.
But he who sees and can, may he grant
recompense.
I now see well, we cannot satisfy our
mind unless it is enlightened by the
truth beyond whose boundary no truth
lies.
Mind, reaching that truth, rests within
it as a beast within its lair. Mind can
attain that truth, if not, all our all
our desires were vain.
Therefore, our our doubting blossoms
like a shoot out from the root of truth.
This natural urge spurs us toward the
peak from height to height.
Lady, my knowing why we doubt invites,
sustains, my reverent asking you about
another truth that is obscure to me.
I want to know if, in your eyes, one can
amend for unkept vows with other acts.
Good works your balance will not lying
too scant.
Then Beatrice looked at me with eyes so
full of sparks of love, eyes so divine
that my own force of sight was overcome,
took flight, and eyes downcast, I almost
lost my senses.
>> Okay, so
um this is very much a student teacher
relationship, right? Where Beatrice is
the teacher and Dante is a student.
And as the teacher, what Beatrice really
wants is for the student to ask
questions, to doubt, to challenge.
Because only through this process can a
student achieve
full understanding, okay?
So,
um
why is Beatrice excited about the
question that Dante asked? Okay, so
we've had this long discussion about
Piccarda,
right? We now know what she did wrong.
And we now know why she is in a lower
sphere.
But then Dante asked this question, and
he asked this question and the question
is,
so she screwed up, okay? She
um
was
taken by the soldiers from the nunnery.
So, she that showed a lack of will.
But is it possible
for her
to redeem herself
by committing acts of charity
so wonderful
that it
redeems her from her lack of will. Does
that make sense, guys?
Like so she she come she's a nun,
Uh, taken away, and now she becomes a
queen, and she's like, "You know what? I
want to be the best queen in the world.
I'm going to give all my wealth to all
the poor people in the world."
That makes sense, right?
What do you guys think? That would would
would that work?
>> But that wouldn't solve the core problem
of her still being fearful of failure,
right? Fearful of
transcending.
>> Okay, can you can you explain some more,
please?
>> The reason why Piccardia was was was not
able to transcend good get to the next
level is because she was fearful at the
core.
In life, in her journey, he's she's
still going to get back to that same
situation where she'll have to choose,
right? Between a rock and a hard place,
right? So, then
if she doesn't have the will to to to
transcend that, then um
you know, you you're still not the next
level, right? You're still not the next
fear.
>> Okay.
Okay, so that's logically correct, yes,
okay? But but but let's go deeper, yes?
>> Yeah, so I was thinking that she cannot
be redeemed by this because
um essentially she is doing all these
like acts of charity
uh for like the result of her redeeming
herself. So, she's not being genuine
about these like acts of kindness,
and I don't think that that's able to
redeem her.
>> Yeah, but who cares?
She's still helping the poor.
>> Yeah, but then that act would not be
like totally good because it would be
for like a selfish purpose.
Like if that makes sense.
>> I I understand, that makes sense. But
I'm I'm trying to logically understand
what's going on. So,
I mean, she
breaks her vow,
then she goes and like
helps a billion people live
happier lives, right? She's a great
queen.
Wouldn't that redeem her in the eyes of
God?
>> Yes, but like
>> No, actually it would not.
The answer is it would not redeem her in
the eyes of God. But I'm I'm trying to
I'm trying to figure out what the
problem is.
>> I guess like my answer to that would be
like she is pushing herself to do a lot
of these things because she's still is
worried that like God is not going to
like forgive her and then that she's
going to end in like a bad circle in
heaven. So, she is still worried. So,
like she's still not like acting upon
that well.
>> Okay, I I don't understand because she
just helped a billion people live
happier lives.
And it's coming from a place of anxiety
and fear. She's afraid that God will
punish her. But the results are good.
So, who cares?
>> Quality over quantity in this case.
>> Can you explain what this means?
>> The [laughter] the the fundamental
nature of her soul or her being of her
existence in her own eyes is always
going to be that as she progresses until
she overcomes this fear of failure. She
can help a billion or trillion,
she'll going to get back to that same
spot.
You're going to have to choose and
you're going to have to choose to
overcome your fears.
>> Okay.
Yes?
>> The way you're posing the question
sounds very
consequentialist with ethics like we
we're caring about the outcome, but this
would have been in in a time of like
Aristotelian virtue ethics and so we
would be caring far more about the four
virtues than
than the outcome.
>> Okay, but but I I I I understand this. I
understand this is a different time, but
I'm saying like
um in the grand scheme of things
if this person, Bakarta, is helping a
billion people live happier lives
who cares what her motivation is?
Who cares why she's doing any of this,
right? I'm saying I'm saying this not in
any con, I'm just saying like generally
speaking, the general principle.
Yeah, yeah?
>> Um, it's the it's the Constantine
argument all over again. So, you watch
the movie Constantine, so Constantine
did some bad things and then he tried to
save himself by doing a lot of good
things. In his case, it was exercising
demons. And he got really mad when God
and his angels can't tell him that oh,
you're going to go to hell anyways. And
he asked the angel, why can't I go to
heaven? And the angel was like, oh, it's
because none of the things you did was
selfless. You see, Ricardo helped all of
these people live better lives, but
these people literally have nothing to
do with her own soul. Like, when God
God is not judgemental. When God looks
at you, let's say when he looks at you,
he he does not see your deeds, he sees
your salvation through your spirit. And
in this case, she has not attained
salvation through her spirit. She has
tried to use good deeds to make up make
up for this, but she has not attained
this.
>> Yeah.
That that is correct, yes.
That is closer to what I want, yes.
Anyone else?
Yes.
>> Yeah, but I think this make me have
question cuz I just want to know the
different between the demon and the God
cuz demon also said that I mean to be
God.
>> So, no more demons?
>> The demons.
>> There are no demons, there's only God.
>> Are there only God, right? So, so
therefore I think the God is out to give
you something for not really return, but
the crane maybe just try to make a deal
with you or maybe just, you know, sign a
track contract or what?
>> Okay, okay guys. Okay, all right. Um, so
we could be here like all day, okay? But
but let me explain what the idea here
is. To understand what's going on,
I need to explain to you
Immanuel Kant's categorical imperative.
Okay? The categorical imperative
by Immanuel Kant.
And there are three principles
to the categorical imperative, which is
the highest moral law in the universe.
Okay? The
rule of life that allows you to be
closer to God.
The categorical imperative, okay? So,
the first idea is
um
you are a reflection
of the universe. So, just imagine that
whatever you do,
the entire universe will do.
If you laugh, the universe laughs with
you. If you are angry, the universe is
angry with you. Okay? So, imagine that
you are just a fractal
or reflection of the entire universe.
And whatever you do, the entire universe
will do as well.
Okay? Now we understand why whatever
Prokofiev does doesn't redeem her.
Because her act
of fear, her act of
incontinence,
of going with the soldiers and not
keeping her vows, it changes the nature
of the universe.
And that doesn't really matter if she
made a billion people richer. Doesn't It
doesn't matter, okay?
The universe is poorer because of her
fear, of her lack of faith. That's
number one. Number two is free will.
Everything you do, you do because it is
your choice. So, back to the original
point, which is like, you know, you're
like, I have to go help help If I go
help a billion people, then I should be
able to go to heaven, right? Or
Constantine says, "Well, I killed a lot
of demons, so therefore I should go to
heaven." That's not the way it works,
okay? Everything you do has to be cut
because of free will.
And the last is
humans
are the ultimate end.
Okay?
You cannot say, "Okay, to save a billion
people, I need to cut out one person."
That goes against the categorical
imperative. I know it sounds stupid.
Wait a minute. I I kill one person, I
save a billion people? You can't do
that, okay? That's not how the universe
works.
Every soul is precious to God. Every
soul is unique to God. Therefore, you
cannot kill another soul in order to
advance a greater good.
Okay? God would never ever ask you to
kill someone else
in order to achieve a higher good.
So, this is the categorical categorical
imperative. And the categorical
imperative is really
a way for us to understand the morality
of Dante's cosmology, of his universe.
Okay, does that make sense? That's why
there's no way for Piccard to redeem
herself in the eyes of God.
All right?
So, this raises an interesting question.
What can Piccard Piccard do to redeem
herself then, according to the
categorical imperative, according to
Dante?
How?
Well, if she becomes queen and she saves
a billion people, that doesn't work. So,
what can she do?
>> She can [snorts] run away and go back to
the nunnery.
>> Yes.
That is a possibility, yes.
>> Uh maybe just sharing as much love as
she can to her like children's.
>> That's no different from making billion
people happier.
Right?
>> Yeah, but it would be more like personal
and like connected to the soul, I guess.
Like uh
cuz also uh giving money to people isn't
really about love uh in a way.
>> Yeah, yeah, but but but why she being
Well, why she loving her children so
much?
Why she Why she so nice to her children
then?
It goes back to the constant in palm,
right?
It's the same thing where constant was
doing a lot of good by killing these
demons and God says, "We don't care."
Same thing where, you know, if
Ricarda has 10 kids and she they all
love her and she loves them back, God's
not going to care either.
The same situation, right? So, I'm
saying like, "What can she do
to redeem herself in the eyes of God?"
Uh yes, and then then you.
Well, if there's no way then there's no
free will.
Right?
So, there has to be a way. Yes?
>> Uh repent.
>> Wow, I'm just asking this question. How
can you repent?
Yes?
>> If there's free will, then her like her
will should be able to change. So, like
instead of wanting to be closer to God
and thus being in a nunnery, she could
change her free will. She change her
will.
>> How? I don't understand.
>> Like her will is now, "I will be a good
king and a good a queen and a good
mother."
>> We just said that. We just said that
doesn't work, right?
>> But that was because she was coming from
a place of fear. If she comes from a
place of
will.
>> Right? And so, okay. So, now what's
happening is that her contingent will is
now harmonizing with her absolute will,
which forces her to do what? Yes?
>> So, this is a
This This is like prosperity gospel,
okay? This is really stupid. This is
really entitled. But what if
Ricarda just stops begging begging God
to like, "Oh God, please notice me."
What if Ricarda goes, "Okay, I am worthy
of this now."
>> Is she begging God for anything?
>> Yeah,
well, the solutions that we just
proposed like doing all these good
deeds, that's a roundabout way of
begging to be honest.
>> But is she doing Was she doing any of
these things?
Is she doing any of these things?
>> Yeah, she isn't.
>> No, she isn't.
What what what is she feeling right now?
Like what is she feeling right now?
She didn't have any
How does she feel?
>> Content.
>> She's feeling content, okay?
So so this all hypothetical. I'm saying
if she really wanted to redeem herself
in the eyes of God, what would she do?
>> Maybe she can increase her will. I do
want to ascend into like a closer space
to God.
>> Exactly, okay. That that that's it,
okay? Do you understand? If all she's
like the way she redeems herself is
saying, "I'm not happy being the dumbest
kid at Yale. I want to be like some
other second second dumbest kid at Yale
or something, okay?"
Anything, who cares? But that wouldn't
make her redeem redeem herself in the
eyes of God. Because now she's actually
saying actually saying more will. When
you do that, you're showing your faith,
love, and trust in God. That's what God
wants. None of this crap like, "Okay,
I'll do it I'll donate a billion dollars
to charity, okay?
Or I'll be really nice to my kids."
Because God doesn't want that crap. God
wants you to
love yourself.
Okay?
So in other words, who really put her in
the lower sphere?
It's ourselves, do you understand? It's
all free will, it's all free choice.
Wherever you are in the universe, it's
because you you choose to be there.
Does that make sense?
No one put you there, okay? When
Picardo says, "God put me here and I'm
thankful to God," she is insulting God.
Okay?
This God would never do that to you.
God would never make you the dumbest kid
at Yale.
All right? If you choose to do that.
Am I talking too much about Yale?
>> THAT'S FINE.
>> [laughter]
>> YEAH.
>> IT makes it more alive.
>> Right.
Sorry about that. All right. Okay.
Um
all right, so let's go on, okay?
>> All right.
If in the fire of love, I seem to flame
beyond the measure visible on Earth,
so that I overcome your vision's forth,
you need not wonder. I'm so because of
my perfected vision. As I grasp the
good, so I approach the good and act.
Indeed, I see that in your intellect now
shines the never-ending light.
Once seen, that light alone and always
kindles love. And if a lesser thing
allure your love, it is a vestige of
that light, which though imperfectly
gleams through that lesser thing.
You wish to know if through a righteous
act one can repair a promise
unfulfilled, so that the soul and God
are reconciled?
So, Beatrice began this canto, and as
one who does not interrupt her speech,
so did her holy reasoning proceed.
The greatest gift, the magnan-
magnanimity of God, as he created, gave
the gift most suited to his goodness,
gifts that he most prizes, was the
freedom of the will.
>> Okay, guys, do you guys see this, okay?
She's saying, because God loves us, he
gives us
free will. That is his greatest gift to
us.
Okay, that's how we know he loves us.
I'm going
>> Those beings that have intellect, all
these and none but these, received and
do receive this gift. Thus, you may draw
as consequence the high worth of a vow
when what is pledged with your consent
encounters God's consent.
For when a pact is drawn between a man
and God, then through free free will, a
man gives up what I have called his
treasure, his free will.
What then can be a fitting compensation?
To use again what you had offered would
mean seeking to do good with ill-gotten
gain.
But now you understand the major point.
But since the Holy Church gives
dispensations which seems in contrast
with the truth I stated, you need to sit
at table somewhat longer. The food that
you have taken was tough food. It still
needs help if you're to digest it.
Open your mind to what I shall disclose
and hold it fast within you. He who
hears but does not hold what he has
heard learns nothing.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, all right. So, let's
try to figure this out, okay? So, Dante
asked this question.
Piccarda
um did
wrong um
but is there a way to to compensate for
what she did? What is Beatrice's answer?
What is the logic here?
Just summarize for me what she's saying.
The logic is this, right?
God loves us and God's greatest gift to
us is
to give us free will.
So, we can do whatever we want.
Okay?
And what did What did Piccard do with
his free will?
Free choice.
>> She didn't do anything.
>> Uh excuse me?
>> With her own free will.
>> She
She promised her free will to God so
that the two are now founded together.
Okay?
So what's happened is that God gave
Piccard her free will and then Piccard
gave her free will to God so that so
that now they are eternally married.
Right? If you're eternally married, you
can't divorce.
You cannot
betray the person, okay? So what Piccard
did was not was not just not keep a vow,
she betrayed God.
Right?
That is what you're just saying. This is
pretty extreme.
Do you guys
Are you guys okay with with this line of
argument?
>> So her mistake was promising her free
will to God?
>> Um
So yes, and what
And and so like do you think
Do you think it's a bit harsh, you
think?
>> Uh
No.
>> Yeah?
>> I I think this is a pretty slippery
slope to slide on.
I I think this is it's a it's a it's a
slope it's it's it's a it's a logical
issue. So you're taking something that's
pretty small and you're blowing up out
of context. Like everything can stand
for something. His
Piccard's vows to God can stand for God
himself.
And if they can stand for God himself,
then he betray then he betray God and
becomes bigger and bigger and that's a
problem.
>> Okay, let
let's use an analogy, okay?
Let's say that
um a man and a wife got married, okay?
It's a marriage.
The wife
betrays
the husband
with some affair.
How could the wife
redeem herself in the eyes of the
husband?
Yeah?
>> Well, actually this is resistive cuz
I think the a loving fair is kind of
third way, right? So if there's third
way, then I think the wife should make
apologize. So the God will forgive the
people who make apologize.
>> Okay, so okay, okay. So your wife cheats
on you
and she apologizes and you're like,
"Fine. I forgive you."
Are you willing to forgive her?
>> Uh
physically, [laughter]
mentally, no.
>> What can she do to
redeem herself in your eyes? If you're
the husband and she cheats on you.
There's no way. I don't think there is.
I don't know, okay?
Right? I mean
If No, okay, let's switch this, okay?
You're you're the wife and the husband
cheats on you.
What could he do to redeem your redeem
himself in your eyes?
What?
>> [laughter]
>> Oh.
Out of battery.
>> Uh yeah, okay.
Uh yeah, there's there's no one over
here, yeah.
>> So, I I wasn't going to say that he can
redeem himself. I was going to say that
he can only be redeemed when I decide
that he is redeemed. Like he has no
choice in the matter. I decide whether
or not he's redeemed.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, go ahead.
>> I I think a better way of framing it is
whoever that cheats, right, the wife or
the husband. In this case, if the
husband cheats, right, how would the
husband be able to redeem himself in the
eyes of himself? As in his own journey,
right, as opposed to relative to what
cuz this is judgment, right? If the wife
needs to judge whether the husband is
redeemed, that's her life. So, in the
eyes of the husband himself who cheated,
how do you get back to that place before
you cheated?
Right? So, I think
I guess the only solution is similar
like you break the cycle. If you find
yourself in a cheating situation again,
if you decide not to cheat, I think
that's
>> Well, no, he already cheated.
>> Or you pretend that you didn't cheat.
>> Well, that's not how it [laughter]
works, man.
>> Well, in your next marriage.
>> Sorry, sorry, sorry, man.
>> Yeah, so
maybe I want to reiterate what she was
thinking because
um
humans aren't God. And so
>> It was what what?
>> Humans aren't God.
>> Yeah, that's right, they're not God.
>> And so but but this is a this is a
judgment that the wife
is dealing with the cheater and she's
trying to regain trust.
But God doesn't have this issue of of
trust.
>> Okay, yeah,
I understand. I understand what's up.
I'm saying like can you give me the
concrete
thing you can do to redeem yourself?
>> Well, you'd change your character and
then you would gain trust by that
changed character. So, someone who
cheats at 18, maybe they don't cheat at
40. So, it just takes time and regain
trust.
>> But but but but how can you regain
trust?
>> By not cheating in the future.
I mean, by being a different person.
You can't go back in time and not and
un-cheat, right? So, all you're going to
do is is find yourself, like he's saying
and like she's saying, you're just not
going to
do it. You're going to be a different
person.
>> What's the problem with cheating? Can
Can Can we first explain why
Look, okay, so you have this random
one-night affair. Who cares?
Why What does it matter?
Yeah?
>> Sure, I think that you know, just like a
Clinton used to say, just have a
I don't have sex relationship with with
the girl. But he said I I I have to have
sex. So, a relationship maybe is is kind
of thing is more than three times
for sex.
>> That is relationship.
>> That is a evil guy, because that is a
for once, I think it's a mistake. It's a
cheating only mistake. It can be
understand.
>> Yeah, yes.
>> Yes.
>> Uh I think the the only way would be if
the party who
sort of committed the sin, did the
cheating,
the
other partner can see that they feel
genuinely uh bad for what they did, cuz
you can cheat and not really care or
just surf the internet.
>> I I understand. I understand all this.
I'm saying like, okay, first let's
establish what cheating does. Why is
cheating a bad thing? Like, who cares?
Yes?
>> Because you have broken a vow or
covenant.
And you have to redeem or pay in blood.
>> What vow?
>> So, if they are married, then it's the
vow that they made before God that
they're going to be men and wife till
death do them part.
>> And And how do they make this vow?
>> In front of God.
>> And And what do they How do they make
this vow?
>> Um at a ceremony.
>> At a ceremony, and what do they do? They
speak it out, right?
>> it and they signed it.
>> They spoke it aloud.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, do you understand?
>> Mhm.
>> All right? So, there's now this bond.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
>> Yes.
>> So, when you cheat, what you're doing is
you're
>> have broken it.
>> You're breaking this bond. That's a
problem. Right?
>> huge thing, especially in a covenant,
right? Because covenant basically means
if you break it, you have to die or pay
the price. I shall be like the animal
that got cut in half. That's the initial
covenant that was in the Bible.
>> That's right. So, what you've done is
you've changed the nature of the
relationship from one based on trust to
one now that is one of suspicion.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
See, that's a problem. The sex is not
the issue. The affair is not the issue.
The The trust is the issue.
Yes?
>> So, I This is why being with God is
better than being with your boyfriend or
girlfriend. Because your boyfriend or
girlfriend cannot read your mind. Like
you can you can try to convince them.
You can kneel on keyboard and you can
tell them, "I've changed. I promise."
But they can choose not to believe you.
But the good thing with God is that he
can see all of you. If you bare yourself
to him, then he can see all of who you
are, all of who you have become. And if
you have truly moved on, if you have
truly become a better person, then he
would know it.
>> Okay.
Let me ask you this question, okay?
Let's imagine you're husband and she and
she cheated on your wife once, okay?
What are you most likely to do next?
Come on, guys.
You'll do it again. And then what?
You'll do it again. You understand?
So, you breaking that vow not only
changes your relationship with your
wife, it changes also who you are, your
understanding of yourself.
Right?
Does that make sense?
That's why breaking a vow is that
serious. It's not like, "Okay, well, I
got drunk and I did something stupid."
No, no, no, no, no. It's you've just
changed your understanding of yourself.
We We can also say you change how God
perceives you. You're like, "Well, God
doesn't really care about cheats. I'll
do it again."
Do you do you understand?
Okay? So, what this is what Donny is
saying. These are very serious things.
If you make a vow
before God and before people, you're
making a contract with yourself.
And if you break this contract,
you'll probably keep on doing it because
it's changed the nature of your soul.
Right? And there is no redemption
for this. There's nothing you can do to
repair this.
Does that make sense?
Okay?
All right.
>> Your answer your question you kept
asking us is what can we do now? And
your answer seems to be nothing.
>> But what's the problem?
What's the problem with
this?
Why is it so serious? Everything else is
like, "Well, you know, if you just want
to change, you'll change." But but this
is really serious. Why?
You've
broken your
>> your vow to God essentially.
>> That's right. And so, what what what
should you not do then?
>> So, I understand that. So, you're just
saying once you've broken your vow, then
then you might as well lay down and die
and go to hell. Go to inferno.
>> Well, no no no no no. The point here is
that
you have free will. So, you can do
whatever you want.
Do not make a vow to God
unless you want to die for it.
>> Sure.
>> Right?
Does that make sense?
There are things you must take
seriously. If you can just speak out
anything you want with with no
consequence,
then
this
universe has no meaning about itself.
>> So, that was your answer, die.
>> Okay. So, let's think about okay?
You've broken your vow to God.
Right?
And now you are in the lowest sphere of
heaven.
What can you do now?
>> I don't I don't think we've come to an
answer.
>> Mhm?
>> Renew the vow.
Okay, okay, all right. All right, so so
let's be precise about this, okay? We we
have like 10 minutes, okay? And and and
we'll we'll let let's really really
try to unpack this.
Okay, so you made this vow to God or to
your wife, okay? And again, don't make
vows unless you're really
serious about it, okay? Guys, don't make
vows unless you can keep them.
All right? No one's going to make you do
these vows. If you're going to make
these vows, you better keep them, all
right?
But then, for whatever reason, you have
broken the vow.
All right? Now, what I want to do is
look into your psychology.
Okay?
How do you explain the fact that you
broke this vow?
What did the picada do?
>> Helplessness. I couldn't do anything
about it.
>> Exactly, right? Like like yeah, I
my wife, but you know, I got drunk and
she raped me, so it wasn't really my
choice.
Okay? So so you say I'm helpless. Then
what happens?
Your psychology.
>> Can't fight himself.
>> All right. So, I want to be precise,
okay? This is really important for you
to understand the Divine Comedy. You do
something that breaks your vows. This
causes you to feel hopeless because you
don't want to take responsibility,
right?
Then what happens? Uh at the back
>> It's kind of like what Eve did, shifting
the blame to the serpent and be like,
"It's him that tempts me. It's not me
that wants to do this." And that's what
Adam did to essentially human.
>> Yeah, it's the same thing, but I'm
saying what happens to Eve
psychologically.
Right? When you blame someone else
>> You lose agency.
And then what happens?
>> Become passive.
>> Me?
>> You become passive.
>> Yeah.
And can you ever change?
>> And you won't be able to change, okay?
That's exactly what what I mean with
Piccarda, right?
She made a vow to God.
Very, very serious, okay? The most
serious thing you can do in your life is
make a vow to God. Nothing else beats
this.
Okay? That's number one. Number two is
she's not able to keep this vow because
she lacks the will, she's afraid, it's
her fault.
She shifts the blame and the
responsibility to her brother.
And then she just imagine herself
as
forever lacking agency.
This makes her passive and it makes her
accept whatever comes her way so that
when she ends up in the lower spheres of
the heaven, she's like, "I'm happy
here." Even though she's probably not
happy there.
You understand?
Okay?
So,
it's not that we can't be redeemed, it's
just like we dig a hole
and we bury ourselves in it so that
it's impossible to redeem ourselves.
Okay?
Does that make sense, guys?
Okay. But this But But this does not
answer the question, right?
What can be done?
Yeah?
>> I think on the topic of agency, first
she has to take back agency. We've
already discussed that.
>> But she can't.
She cannot take back agency. Why?
Because her entire worldview
is based on her lack of agency. Do you
understand?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> to explain herself why she didn't
resist. The answer is she had no agency.
And her And so she's like,
"We We God doesn't give us agency.
God demands our obedience."
Do you understand?
>> Yeah, but
>> But so with her worldview, it's not
impossible for her to exercise agency
because agency is defined as God.
>> Then change her worldview.
>> But you cannot change your worldview
because it's your worldview.
It's like telling telling a computer,
"Change your
software."
It's your programming.
>> Knowledge. Knowledge. Like uh if we want
an AI to change their worldview, if we
want an AI to change their views, then
we feed them a lot of that kind of
knowledge and the AI changes its views.
Or she can just go take DMT.
>> Excuse me?
>> She can just go take a DMT and
>> And make what?
>> DMT
I want to take a
I'm not changing her worldview.
>> But she's already in heaven, huh?
>> No.
>> That does no good in heaven.
Uh yes, did Did you uh
>> I'm so wanting to be closer to God, I
guess. Like repent and move on.
Or the whole lamb of God [clears throat]
wash away the sin and then move on. I
don't know.
>> Who is the
most important person who has ever
lived?
Jesus, right?
Why is he important?
Why is he so consequential? Why do you
have two billion people believe in
Jesus?
Why?
>> [snorts]
>> What what what does that mean?
>> He can bring us salvation.
>> Right, okay. So, does it make sense?
>> [clears throat]
>> Jesus is so consequential because he
provides a solution
to an impossible problem, which is how
do you redeem yourself?
Right? Because often you're in trouble
because you think you deserve your fate.
And for someone to come along and says
that I forgive you unconditionally,
I redeem you unconditionally, that's the
most that's the that's the most powerful
idea in the universe, okay? So, so I
know it's not satisfactory, but one
possible solution is for someone else to
forgive you.
>> Oh.
>> Because you can't forgive yourself.
Right?
>> So, what you're basically saying is that
she has to wait for someone else to save
her.
>> And who would forgive her?
>> Jesus.
>> And who is Jesus?
>> Yeah.
>> God, right?
And will God forgive you?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. If you turn towards God, God will
always forgive you.
So, it's a question of faith, do you
understand?
Like, as long as you have the right
faith, you can always change
for the better because you know that God
will always forgive you.
Okay? So, that's the solution.
All right? The solution is to turn
towards God because you will never find
the solution yourself. It's impossible
because
your worldview, right? You just come to
to the idea that no, I'm helpless. I
must obey God, and God wants me just to
be here for the rest of the rest of my
life for all eternity.
Okay?
Right?
Does that make sense, guys?
>> Yeah.
>> And and any more
questions? Yes?
>> Yeah, so I think what you have said just
reminded me of the memory I always
cherish Christianity the believer who
said that don't always try to be like a
king. If you want to be king, then if
you do something wrong, then you have
it's very hard to to forgive yourself.
But if if you just you know,
let God to to to to sit
on your on your seat, rule your seat,
then you can you can be forgiven.
>> Yeah, okay.
So, this is something that's really hard
for us to appreciate, but our actions
change our character.
You understand? If you commit sin, it's
not like oh, you feel really bad and
like you won't do it again. No, it's
like once you commit sin, you begin to
rationalize the sin.
And you do more of it, okay? And then
the sin eventually consumes you, and
that's how you end up in hell. Hell does
not exist outside of us. Hell is a
mental construct.
It's a way for us to explain away
our actions.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
All right, yes?
>> So, hell is not taking responsibility
and not [clears throat]
forgiving yourself.
>> Uh hell is not forgiving yourself.
Yes, exactly. That's what hell literally
is. Not forgiving yourself, and we'll
see that when we actually go back and
visit the inferno, okay?
All right? But, it's important that we
first start off with
uh paradise, so we understand the
cosmology.
Okay?
Uh any more questions, guys?
Okay. So, so that's it for the first
day. We have another couple minutes. So,
um
let me talk about how you can make the
most out of your experience today, okay?
So, the first thing I will say is you
guys need to go back and review what we
just read today, okay?
Trust me, if you do this,
you're going to have a lot more insight
into Dante, okay? So, we've had this
this amazing four-day discussion. We've
read a lot, uh thanks to to Carol. Um
but, go back and review for yourself.
Read for yourself the first
four
cantos, and make sure you understand
everything, okay? If there's something
you don't understand, come tomorrow with
questions.
All right? Just make sure you review
today, come tomorrow with questions.
All right? So, we'll spend the first
part of of tomorrow morning just
answering any questions you have
about uh
Dante.
All right? Make sure you understand
everything. If there's a reference you
don't understand, like who is Glaucus,
who is
Daphne, go Make sure you understand this
stuff. Okay? Just read read up on it.
Um and the third thing I will say is
always trust your intuition and your
imagination.
If it feels right to you, it's probably
right. If it feels wrong to you, it's
probably wrong, okay?
So, if it feels wrong to you,
say it. Be honest. Challenge me. Correct
me, okay? Be like
And the thing about Beatrice and Dante,
right? They're in heaven and what do
they do? They argue. They debate. They
question each other.
Okay?
Excuse me?
>> Such a great married relationship.
>> Uh yes, okay.
Uh yes.
Um no. Yeah, that that's exactly right,
okay?
All right. So, so that's that but like
the but like how Beatrice and Dante
interact with each other, I hope that
this can also be like that. Okay, our
classroom can also be one of constant
questioning, debate,
uh open and honest dialogue. All right.
Okay, guys. So, that's great. That's it
for today. I will see everyone tomorrow.
We start at 10:00, okay?
Okay, thanks.